<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Dying man's assistant, or, Short instructions for those who are concern'd in the preparing of sick persons for death being also no less worthy the consideration of all good Christians in time of health, as shewing the importance of an early preparation for their latter end, with regard as well to their temporal, as eternal state ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 164 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37135</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2954</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17100</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13371264</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13371264</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99316</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37135)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99316)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 787:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Dying man's assistant, or, Short instructions for those who are concern'd in the preparing of sick persons for death being also no less worthy the consideration of all good Christians in time of health, as shewing the importance of an early preparation for their latter end, with regard as well to their temporal, as eternal state ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 128 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Lawrence ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Death --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99316:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99316:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Dying Man's Aſſiſtant:</hi> OR, Short Inſtructions For thoſe who are concern'd in the <hi>Preparing of Sick Perſons</hi> FOR DEATH.</p>
            <p>Being alſo No leſs Worthy the Conſideration of all Good <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in time of <hi>Health.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As ſhewing the Importance of an Early <hi>Preparation</hi> for their <hi>Latter End;</hi> with regard as well to their <hi>Temporal,</hi> as <hi>Eternal State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>O that they were wiſe, that they underſtood this, that they would conſider their latter end!</hi> Deut. 32. 29.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Lawrence</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in the <hi>Poultry.</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:99316:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99316:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>dging the <hi>SUBJECT</hi> of this <hi>TREATISE</hi> above the needing any <hi>Arguments</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the World of its <hi>Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance;</hi> I ſhall trouble the <hi>REA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER</hi> with no other <hi>PREFACE,</hi> than may juſt ſuffice for the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitating his <hi>Application</hi> of it to <hi>Practice.</hi> Nor to this purpoſe do I think any thing more neceſſary, than the imprinting in his mind a clear and ſuccinct <hi>Idea</hi> of its <hi>Deſign.</hi> Which in ſhort is this.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:99316:3"/>
            <p>The whole, being intended for <hi>A Compleat Set of</hi> Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>ſhewing how to aſſiſt and diſpoſe a</hi> Sick Perſon, <hi>in order to his making a Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py End,</hi> is divided into <hi>XVIII. Chapters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Firſt of which I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to the <hi>MINISTER,</hi> the <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> the <hi>Humility</hi> and <hi>Sincerity,</hi> the <hi>Patience</hi> and <hi>Attention,</hi> the <hi>Prudence</hi> and <hi>Conduct,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd on his part, towards the due <hi>Performance</hi> of this <hi>SACRED OFFICE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>gh the Body of the <hi>Work,</hi> I have conſider'd the <hi>SICK
<pb facs="tcp:99316:3"/> PERSON</hi> under all the various. <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue</hi> or <hi>Frailty,</hi> incident to <hi>Mankind</hi> in that Condition; and have attempted to lay down the moſt proper and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual Means for improving the <hi>One,</hi> and removing the <hi>Other;</hi> whether by force of <hi>Argument,</hi> or manner of <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication</hi> and <hi>Addreſs:</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in great diſtinction is to be made, according to the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent <hi>Quality, Capacity,</hi> and <hi>Temper</hi> of the <hi>PATIENT.</hi> In a Word, the <hi>MINISTER</hi> has here, ready digeſted (and ia Terms for the moſt part ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the <hi>SCRIPTURE,</hi> or <hi>FATHERS</hi>) Forms of <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Ejaculations,</hi> both
<pb facs="tcp:99316:4"/> for his own <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe and the <hi>SICK PERSON</hi>'s; with whatever elſe I judged conducive to the ſtating a good <hi>Chriſtian</hi> in a perfect Readineſs for his <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution;</hi> having therein had ſo much regard to his <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral</hi> Affairs, in conjunction with his <hi>Spiritual,</hi> as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the providing (by a prudent, juſt, and timely <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal</hi> of his <hi>Eſtate</hi>) for his doing <hi>Right</hi> to <hi>All, Good</hi> to as <hi>Many</hi> as may be, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Amity</hi> in his <hi>Family.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Laſtly, As the <hi>PATIENT</hi>'s <hi>Illneſs</hi> ſhall terminate in his <hi>Death,</hi> or <hi>Recovery,</hi> I have made it the <hi>Subject</hi> of the
<pb facs="tcp:99316:4"/> XVIII Chapter, to ſhew the <hi>MINISTER,</hi> how to improve both Events to <hi>Edification;</hi> the former with reſpect to the <hi>Standers by,</hi> the latter to the <hi>Perſon Recover'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>WHICH Inſtructions</hi> tho' I have all along directed to the <hi>MINISTER,</hi> as falling within his proper <hi>Province;</hi> yet would I by no means be underſtood, to reſtrain them to his uſe alone; there being, God knows, too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Accidents</hi> in the way of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing his <hi>Aſſiſtance,</hi> to put the <hi>Patient</hi>'s <hi>Everlaſting Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> upon that <hi>Iſſue.</hi> Thus far only I would urge it; that when by any reaſonable <hi>Endeavours,</hi> the <hi>Miniſter</hi>'s <hi>Aid</hi> may be procured,
<pb facs="tcp:99316:5"/>
'tis without Diſpute, to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd: But that failing, it is not barely allow'd to, but incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent on every good <hi>Chriſtian</hi> (whether Relation, Friend, or other beſt qualified for it) to put in Practice any ſuch Part of this <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> as he ſhall think may moſt avail the <hi>SICK PERSON</hi> in his <hi>Laſt Minutes;</hi> with Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception only to the <hi>Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the <hi>Holy Sacrament</hi> of the <hi>LORD's SUPPER,</hi> which the <hi>Church</hi> has thought fit, from a due regard to the Sacredneſs thereof, to reſerve to herſelf; not doubting, but through the <hi>Mercy</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> the <hi>Perſon</hi> deſiring it, will, in ſuch Caſe, reap e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual <hi>Benefit</hi> from his good <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:99316:5"/> as if he actually <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived</hi> the ſame.</p>
            <p>And this being ſaid; methinks there ſhould need nothing more, to perſwade any one that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of his endeavouring to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der himſelf capable of diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Duty; were it meerly in <hi>Charity</hi> to his <hi>Neighbour,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out other <hi>Motive</hi> thereto. But when to that, ſhall be added the yet further <hi>Conſiderations,</hi> of his being alſo taught hereby, not only how to regulate his own Life, whilſt in <hi>Health,</hi> ſo as to leave little to be done, when it ſhall pleaſe God to viſit him with the like Summons; but even of this <hi>Little,</hi> to know how then more readily to acquit himſelf, by
<pb facs="tcp:99316:6"/> being prepared to make the beſt Advantage of the <hi>MINISTER</hi>'s <hi>Aſſiſtance,</hi> Or Laſtly, under the want of <hi>that,</hi> to be able to make his own <hi>Peace</hi> with <hi>GOD, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he go hence, and be no more ſeen:</hi> I ſay, when all theſe Conſiderations ſhall be duly weigh'd; I cannot ſuppoſe it poſſible for him to doubt, its being a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern of the <hi>Laſt Importance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What remains is, <hi>Chriſtian Reader,</hi> that with the ſame ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, wherewith I have thus en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to repreſent to you, the <hi>Deſign</hi> and <hi>Uſe</hi> of this little <hi>Tract,</hi> I alſo own the many Defects and Frailties of its <hi>Author.</hi> Diverſe <hi>Repetitions</hi> may appear therein leſs grateful to you, and which I will not preſume to ſay, were
<pb facs="tcp:99316:6"/> impoſſible to be avoided. But I doubt not of your thinking more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably of them, when you ſhall conſider, that the <hi>Whole</hi> is not to be us'd at once, but ſuch <hi>Part</hi> only as ſhall be found moſt applicable to the Condition of the <hi>Patient;</hi> not to mention, how little unmindful I have been, on this Account, of making <hi>References</hi> from one <hi>Chapter</hi> to another, where the Diſcourſe would admit it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out interruption. The reſt you are deſired by your <hi>Charity</hi> to excuſe and ſupply; carrying it all along in your Thoughts, that the Chief <hi>Intent</hi> of this <hi>Work</hi> was, the <hi>GLORY</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> and <hi>SALVATION</hi> of <hi>MEN</hi>'s <hi>SOULS:</hi> For which therefore, as I am not much in pain about
<pb facs="tcp:99316:7"/> your <hi>Cenſure,</hi> ſo neither do I ask your <hi>Thanks;</hi> but only to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member'd in your <hi>Prayers,</hi> as you ſhall always be in mine; Who am your <hi>Fellow-Chriſtian</hi> and Faithful <hi>Servant</hi> in the <hi>LORD.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:99316:7"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS OF THE CHAPTERS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Chap. I. <hi>THE Duty of a</hi> Miniſter <hi>in aſſiſting</hi> Perſons <hi>who are in danger of</hi> Death. Pag. 1</item>
               <item>Chap. II. <hi>What things are requiſite for the diſpoſing a</hi> Sick Perſon <hi>to die well.</hi> p. 8.</item>
               <item>Chap. III. <hi>Advice to be given to a</hi> Sick Perſon <hi>concerning his</hi> Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>his</hi> Body, <hi>and his</hi> Eſtate. p. 20.</item>
               <item>Chap. IV. <hi>What the</hi> Miniſter'<hi>s Duty is, when he finds the</hi> Sick Perſon <hi>has not done all that is neceſſary for him, in order to his dying as a good</hi> Chriſtian. p. 26.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:99316:8"/>
               <item>Chap. V. <hi>How</hi> Sick Perſons, <hi>eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſuch as are not very perfect in their</hi> Belief, <hi>ought to be exercis'd in the</hi> Faith. p. 30.</item>
               <item>Chap. VI. <hi>How the</hi> Miniſter <hi>is to raiſe and exerciſe the</hi> Hope <hi>of the</hi> Sick Perſon. p. 34.</item>
               <item>Chap. VII. <hi>The Means for exciting</hi> Charity <hi>in a</hi> Sick Perſon. p. 49.</item>
               <item>Chap. VIII. <hi>What the</hi> Miniſter <hi>is to do, when coming to a</hi> Sick Perſon, <hi>he finds every thing already done, neceſsary for the diſpoſing him to die as a good</hi> Chriſtain. p. 57.</item>
               <item>Chap. IX. <hi>What means are to be us'd when the</hi> Patient <hi>does not reſign him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as he ought, to the Will of God, and is afraid of</hi> Death <hi>through a too great</hi> Love <hi>of this</hi> Life. p. 68.</item>
               <item>Chap. X. <hi>What is to be ſaid to a</hi> Sick Perſon, <hi>whoſe unwillingneſs to die proceeds from an exceſſive Love for the Things of this World.</hi> p. 77.</item>
               <item>Chap. XI. <hi>What is to be done to a</hi> Sick Perſon <hi>that is</hi> Impatient. p. 84.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:99316:8"/>
               <item>Chap. XII. <hi>How thoſe</hi> Perſons <hi>ought to be managed, that lie under</hi> Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations <hi>againſt the</hi> Faith. p. 89.</item>
               <item>Chap. XIII. <hi>How to comfort a</hi> Sick Perſon <hi>that is miſtruſtful of</hi> God'<hi>s</hi> Mercy, <hi>and troubled with</hi> Deſpair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Thoughts. p. 94.</item>
               <item>Chap. XIV. <hi>What is to be ſaid to ſuch as ſhew too great a Confidence, and preſume too far upon their</hi> Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. p. 101.</item>
               <item>Chap. XV. <hi>How a</hi> Sick Perſon <hi>is to be managed, when bereft in a great meaſure, of his</hi> Senſes <hi>and</hi> Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. p. 104.</item>
               <item>Chap. XVI. <hi>What the</hi> Miniſter <hi>is to do, when he finds the</hi> Sick Perſon <hi>poſeſs'd of his</hi> Speech <hi>and</hi> Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, <hi>but likely to die very ſoon.</hi> p. 107.</item>
               <item>Chap. XVII. <hi>How the</hi> Miniſter <hi>is to apply himſelf to a</hi> Sick Perſon, <hi>who has the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of his</hi> Reaſon, <hi>but no Diſpoſition to ſuch things, as are neceſſary to the making a Happy End.</hi> p. 109.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:99316:9"/>
               <item>Chap. XVIII. <hi>What in the laſt place the</hi> Miniſter <hi>is to do, if the</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient <hi>dies; and What, in caſe it ſhall pleaſe</hi> God <hi>to reſtore him to his</hi> Health <hi>again: With regard on the one hand, to the</hi> Standers-by; <hi>and on the other, to the</hi> Perſon Recover'd. p. 117.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Being concluded with A</hi> Prayer <hi>and</hi> Thankſgiving <hi>to be offer'd to GOD, by One newly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd from a Dangerous</hi> Sickneſs. p. 124.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99316:9"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Dying Man's Aſſiſtant:</hi> OR, Short Inſtructions For thoſe who are concern'd in the <hi>Preparing of Sick Perſons</hi> FOR DEATH.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The <hi>Duty</hi> of a <hi>Miniſter</hi> in aſſiſting <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> who are in danger of <hi>Death.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THOSE whom it ſhall pleaſe <hi>Almighty God</hi> to call to the Aſſiſtance of <hi>Dying Chriſtians,</hi> in order to their making a Happy End, ought well to conſider, that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99316:10"/> this is an Office of the higheſt Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; for as much as no leſs than our <hi>Neighbour's Salvation</hi> may depend there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>As we die but once; ſo if in the laſt moment of our Lives, we omit ought that is neceſſary to our Eternal Welfare, we are gone for ever; the Fault is irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable. And what ſhould ſtill the more excite the Zeal and Charity of <hi>Miniſters</hi> on this Occaſion is, this Conſideration, That oftentimes the <hi>Divine Providence</hi> marks out ſome particular Perſons to contribute to the Salvation of others, who without their Aſſiſtance, might e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally periſh. But though this were not ſo; certain it is, that they who are aiding to <hi>Dying Perſons,</hi> may perform their <hi>Duty</hi> in ſuch a manner, as to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them at leaſt, to die in more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant Grace, and contribute to their enjoying a greater degree of Felicity in Heaven. If it be an Act of Charity to preſerve in Grace thoſe that are in Health, by exhorting them to a fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Participation of the <hi>Bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and the Uſe of other Pious Means; What ought the <hi>Miniſter</hi>'s Zeal to be, in aſſiſting thoſe poor Souls that are drawing near the time of their Depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99316:10"/> it being certain, that whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Tree ſhall fall, be it on the South, or be it on the North, there it will for ever lie?</p>
               <p>Let the <hi>Miniſter</hi> therefore remember, that of himſelf he is by no means capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of performing this important <hi>Part</hi> of his <hi>Miniſtry;</hi> but muſt apply himſelf to God for the Aſſiſtance of his Holy Spirit herein. <hi>A Sick Perſon</hi> has often-times his Mind diſturb'd through the violence of his Diſtemper, and ſometimes a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Hell too raiſes in him an inward Terror and Diſquiet; and whil'ſt he is in this Agony, and juſt upon the point of giving up the Ghoſt, the Devil n'ere fails to uſe all his Arts for improving the little time that remains, to his final De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. The Conſideration of all which ſhould oblige the <hi>Miniſter,</hi> hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to acknowledge his own Weakneſs, to be miſtruſtful of his own Strength, and repoſe in God alone, all his Hopes of contributing to the <hi>Salvation</hi> of <hi>Dying Perſons.</hi> His intention of aſſiſting them in the Condition they are in, muſt be ſincere; remembring they are the <hi>Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Members</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who has redeemed them with his <hi>Blood,</hi> and appointed him in his ſtead to take
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99316:11"/> care of their <hi>Salvation;</hi> and that by how much the better <hi>End</hi> they make, ſo much the more God will be glorified. Let all theſe Motives ſerve to raiſe in him a fervent deſire of ſaving them, by all the Means the <hi>Divine Providence</hi> ſhall inſpire him with.</p>
               <p>Let him every day ask of God the Talent neceſſary for this Function. Let him pray for the <hi>Sick</hi> in general, and particularly for thoſe to whom he is called. Let him renew his Zeal by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultations of the Heart, and ſhort and frequent Ejaculations, which he may apply to them; and let him recommend their <hi>Souls</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> not only in his private Prayers, but above all, in the Publick <hi>Prayers</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis adviſable, that the <hi>Miniſter</hi> think afore-hand of what he is to ſay or do on this Occaſion, and ſo to order and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it in his memory, as to omit no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that may be neceſſary, both for the Comfort of the <hi>Sick Perſon,</hi> and Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of thoſe that are preſent. This he ought to be very intent upon; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as the ſame things are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways proper to be ſaid, or at leaſt not to be ſaid in the ſame manner; but muſt be ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>efully ſuited to Time and Place, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99316:11"/> the Diſpoſition he ſhall find in the <hi>Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,</hi> of hearing them. A Perſon of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity is to be dealt with after a quite diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent manner from one of a low Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. They that abound with Wit and Learning, and are of a ſweet Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and have exerciſed themſelves in the Practice of Devotion, are not to be addreſſed to in the ſame Stile, as thoſe that are ignorant, rude, and of a mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſe Nature. To the former, a few Words well choſen, and ſeaſonably ſpoken, are ſufficient: Whereas the latter need common things to be ſaid to them, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dapted to their Apprehenſions; and thoſe to be alſo inlarged upon. But here the <hi>Miniſter</hi> is to conſider; whether they retain, or have loſt their Sences; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their Diſtemper puts them to great Torment, or not; whether they may for ſome time be ſpoken to, or whether their Pain will not permit it. All which ſhews, that there is a great deal of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence requiſite in the <hi>Miniſter,</hi> for his making a good and ſeaſonable uſe of thoſe Things he has prepar'd; ſpeaking them ſometimes interruptedly and by intervals, ſometimes ſoftly, and at other times in a different tone; to the end the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> may the better reliſh them,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99316:12"/> be leſs troubled therewith, and reflect on the ſame with more leiſure. He may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo propound Queſtions to him, if he perceives in him Strength and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding enough to anſwer them. And above all, he muſt not omit Praying by him, and cauſing thoſe that are preſent to join with him therein. In ſhort, let his whole Diſcourſe be plain, tender, and affectionate, particularly with Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Piety and Underſtanding, who are not to be ſpoke to by way of Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but as it were only to refreſh their Minds with thoſe Virtues they have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready known and practis'd.</p>
               <p>But if the <hi>Miniſter</hi> has no knowledge of, or acquaintance with the <hi>Sick Perſon,</hi> the firſt thing he is to do, when he goes to his Houſe, is to get information con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning him, with reſpect to the Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Circumſtances above mention'd; <hi>Viz.</hi> Whether he be a Man of Learning, or not; Whether of a meek and ſweet Nature; whether he has ſtill his Senſes good, and the uſe of his Reaſon; Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he is at the point of Death; Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he has been already viſited by any other <hi>Miniſter,</hi> and has receiv'd the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred <hi>Viaticum:</hi> What Courſe of Life he has led; Whether there be any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99316:12"/> thing of which he ought to be put in mind, neceſſary to his Salvation; Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he lies under any ſecret trouble or affliction; and whether he has his Hearing ſo good, as to be able to hear what may be ſpoken ſoftly to him.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as the <hi>Miniſter</hi> is come into the <hi>Sick Perſon's</hi> Chamber, let him begin his Exhortation with greeting him in an affectionate manner; that ſo by his Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility he may render himſelf the more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable and welcome to him. Then, if he finds it convenient, he may ask him ſome Queſtions about the State of his Conſcience; but this he muſt do gently, and with a modeſt liberty. And when the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> ſhall give him Anſwers, he ought to hear him patiently; taking care not to diſturb him with any Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe forrein to the purpoſe, or with vain repetitions. And thus having made himſelf acquainted with his Temper and Diſpoſition of Mind, let him not omit any thing of Gentleneſs, Tenderneſs, or the like, that may win the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> to a Confidence in him; whereby he may the more eaſily perſwade him of what he ſhall ſay, and in caſe he be oblig'd to come again, the <hi>Patient</hi> may receive him with pleaſure and delight.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:99316:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> What things are requiſite for the diſpoſing a <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> to die well.</head>
               <p>THEY are two-fold. Some abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary; which are ſuch as may put him into a State of Grace: Others, only uſeful to the comforting him and ſtrengthening his Hope. To which is to be added, the Diſpoſal of his Body, and of his Eſtate for the benefit of his Relations. And though there are dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent ways of effecting this, according to the Condition he is in, and the time he has for it; yet we ſhall hereafter treat thereof, as if he had all the leiſure he could deſire for the ſame; and from thence ſhall proceed to ſpeak of what he ought to do, when he wants time, and his Underſtanding grows weaker.</p>
               <p>What therefore the <hi>Miniſter</hi> is princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally to take care of is, to put the <hi>Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> into a State of Grace: To which end, he ought to diſpoſe him to the receiving of the Bleſſed Sacrament of the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> which is the Channel whereby the Holy Ghoſt deſcends into our hearts.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99316:13"/> He muſt alſo read to him ſome proper Places in the Goſpel, and the Service for the Sick: And that done, he may go on to the asking him Queſtions, and let his Diſcourſe fall upon his Diſtemper; inſinuating to him, that the Phyſicians are apprehenſive of his Life; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſhould not rely too much upon Human Means, or what Help his Friends and Relations can give him; but put his whole Truſt and Confidence in God: Who loving him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with an unbounded Love, and being able to do all things, will (if it be for the good of his Soul) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore him to his Health again; or elſe afford him thoſe means whereby he may attain to Everlaſting Bliſs. That he ought with all his heart to turn himſelf towards <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> his moſt true Friend, whoſe Love to him extended ſo far, as to the ſhedding even his Blood for him; as himſelf expreſſeth it in his Holy Goſpel: Who is the only Faithful Friend, that never abandons us at the point of Death; whereas our other Friends either will not, or cannot in that laſt moment be of any avail to us. Who is alſo a Wiſe <hi>Phyſician;</hi> that is able not only to cure the Body, ſo as to continue it ſtill in life for many Years; but even to heal the Soul
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99316:14"/> too, and make it happy for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
               <p>Having thus ſpoken to him, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on inlarg'd according to his diſcretion, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhould in the next place ask him, whether he has any thing which troubles his Conſcience, and ought to be reveal'd; ſo that, if he finds his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper to be violent and dangerous, he may admoniſh him forthwith to disbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then himſelf by Confeſſion. But if he be in no preſent danger of Death, he may be allow'd more time for it; to the end he may the better recollect him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of all he has done amiſs, and heartily beg God's pardon for the ſame; the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter putting him in mind, of the Words of the Prophet to this purpoſe, <hi>In the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs of my Soul, O Lord, will I call to remembrance before Thee all the Years that I have ſpent in Sin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in caſe the <hi>Patient</hi> deſires no time to examine himſelf, and the <hi>Miniſter</hi> knows, that this is only to avoid the trouble of ſearching his Conſcience; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps out of fear that in reflecting upon his ſinful Life paſt, he may unhappily meet with ſome new Temptation, or at the beſt, not reap much fruit there-from; he ought to perſwade him, that to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99316:14"/> in Grace, he muſt without delay make an humble Confeſſion of all his Sins to Almighty God, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Advice of the Son of <hi>Sirach</hi> in his <hi>Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> not defer his Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from day to day: Foraſmuch as we cannot promiſe to our ſelves one hour longer; and that according to our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, or Obdurateneſs of Heart, we ſhall be for ever happy or miſerable. On which occaſion let the <hi>Miniſter</hi> remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber him of what the Wiſeman ſaith, <hi>That delay of Converſion has been the Deſtruction of many Sinners, who flattering themſelves with the hopes of long life, often fall into a Delirium, and loſe their Senſes, or elſe are ſurpris'd by a ſudden Death;</hi> and ſo being prevented of time and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to repent, are irrecoverably loſt; adding, that he who is not ready to be converted to day, will be leſs ſo to morrow. In ſhort, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ought to ſtir him up to a true Contrition of heart, by repreſenting to him the hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſneſs of his Sins; yet with ſuch mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, as not to affright him and caſt him into Deſpair. It will be ſufficient, that he make him ſenſible of the Majeſty of that God he has offended, before whom the Angels themſelves tremble;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99316:15"/> of his inflexible Juſtice, which ſeverely puniſhes the Devils and all Reprobates; and no leſs of his Holineſs, that bears ſo great a hatred to Sin, that whoever dies in impenitence, though formerly he may have led a Righteous Life, muſt expect to be adjudg'd to Everlaſting Flames.</p>
               <p>Yet let the <hi>Miniſter,</hi> as is ſaid before, take care not to affright the <hi>Patient,</hi> eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if he be naturally timorous; but rather increaſe and ſupport his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, by laying before him God's Mercies and Goodneſs, in the order both of Nature and Grace; ſhewing him what great Love He had for him, in not ſparing his only begotten Son, but delivering him up to the Death of the Croſs for the Redemption of him and all penitent Sinners; What Glory He has prepar'd for him in Heaven: How good and gracious He is, and worthy of our Love and Praiſe, who has both made him out of nothing, and adopted him in his Son and our Redeemer <hi>Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi> And ſo the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhall continue with an affectionate tenderneſs to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to him, that this is that Good God he has offended by his manifold Sins; and for which therefore he ought ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to be afflicted and heartily repent.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:99316:15"/>
               <p>Which having ſaid, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> may here make a pauſe, and give the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> time to reflect upon what he has now ſpoken, ſo as he may be excited to Contrition. And then he ſhall raiſe his Hope again, and animate his Love, by telling him, that the ſame God forgives him all his Sins, who in his infinite Mercy waited for his Repentance; and has promiſed by his Prophet, that at what time ſoever the Sinner ſhall return to Him, He will pardon his iniquities, and remember them no more: That his Saviour has his Arms ſtretched out upon the Croſs ready to embrace him, and put him into the poſſeſſion of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, which He has purchaſed for him with his Precious Blood. After this let the <hi>Miniſter</hi> exhort him to ſay both with Heart and Mouth, as the <hi>Publican</hi> in the Goſpel, <hi>Lord, have mercy upon me, a poor Sinner!</hi> And with <hi>David, Lord! forgive me all my Sins. Have mercy upon me O Lord! according to thy great Goodneſs; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the multitude of thy Mercies, do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way mine Offences. Waſh me throughly from my Wickedneſs, and cleanſe me from my Sin. O turn thee unto me, and have mercy upon me; for I am deſolate and in miſery. Againſt Thee, O my God! have I ſinn'd, and done
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99316:16"/> evil in thy ſight. And if thou, Lord, wilt be extream to mark what I have done amiſs, I cannot abide it. O enter not into Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with thy Servant; for in thy ſight ſhall no man living be juſtified. My ſoul cleaves unto the duſt, O quicken thou me according to thy Word. I am full of heavineſs, becauſe I have offended thee. My Soul alſo is ſore troubled; but Lord how long wilt thou pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh me? O be thou merciful unto me, and help me; for I put my truſt in Thee. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member not, O Lord! the Sins and Offences of my Youth; but according to thy mercy think thou upon me. Turn thy face from my Sins, and put out all my miſdeeds. O let me hear of joy and gladneſs, that the bones which thou haſt broken may rejoyce! Make me a clean heart, O God, and renew a right ſpirit withinme. Caſt me not away from thy preſence, and take not thy Holy Spirit from me. O give me the comfort of thy help again, and ſtabliſh me with thy free Spirit. Lord! I am thine, O ſave me and deliver me! Shew the light of thy counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance upon me. Make haſt to help me, O Lord! Thou art my Helper and my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer; O Lord, make no long tarrying. Caſt me not away in this time of diſtreſs; forſake me not now my ſtrength fails me, but draw nigh unto my ſoul, and ſave it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99316:16"/> for thy mercies ſake. Bow down thine Ear, O Lord, and hear me, for I am poor and in miſery. Be merciful unto me, O Lord, for my ſpirit waxeth faint. Comfort the ſoul of thy ſervant, for unto thee, O Lord, do I lift up my ſoul. For thou Lord! art good and gracious, and of great mercy unto all them that call upon thee Give ear, Lord! unto my Prayer, and ponder the voice of my humble deſires. In the time of my trouble I will call upon Thee, for Thou heareſt me. Teach me thy way, O Lord, and I will walk in thy Truth. O knit my heart unto Thee, that I may fear thy Name. Lord, Thou knowest all my deſire and my groaning is not hid from Thee. My heart panteth, my ſtrength has failed me, and the ſight of my Eyes is gone from me. There is no health in my fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of thy diſpleaſure; neither is there any reſt in my bones by reaſon of my Sin. Take thy plague away from me; I am even con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed by the means of thy heavy hand. O hide not thou thy face from me; nor caſt thy Servant away in diſpleaſure. Thou haſt been my ſuccour; leave me not, neither for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake me, O God of my Salvation. Hear my prayer, O Lord, and with thine ears conſider my calling. Hold not thy peace at my tears. For thy hand is heavy upon me day and night; and my moiſture is like the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99316:17"/> drought in ſummer. O ſpare me a little that I may recover my ſtrength, before I go hence, and be no more ſeen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Divine Sentences, or ſome of them, or the like (with which the Book of Pſalms is abounding) the <hi>Miniſter</hi> may uſe, according as he ſhall judge moſt proper and ſuitable to the Capacity of the <hi>Sick Perſon,</hi> and the Condition he ſhall find him in; to the end he may ſtill keep him in a ſtate of Contrition, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move from his heart all inclinations to Sin. But, as we have intimated before, let him take great care, that this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition of his be not imperfect, and grounded only upon fear of Puniſhment; but be excited and ſupported by a true Love of God, and perfect Charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all Men. And when the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> ſhall perceive the <hi>Patient</hi> to be thus throughly affected with the ſenſe of his Sins, and to expreſs a hearty Sorrow for them, and fervent Love towards his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended Creator, let him for his Comfort declare to him, <hi>In the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> that upon his ſincere Repentance all his Sins are done away, and will never more be remembred; That the Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Merciful God has paſſed by,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99316:17"/> and forgiven his Iniquities and Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, has now received him into his Favour, and will ſhortly admit him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Company of his Holy Angels and Bleſſed Saints; That He will make him ſit at Table with him in the Kingdom of Glory; and repleniſh him with Joy and Felicity for ever more.</p>
               <p>But before this Declaration be made, 'tis neceſſary that the <hi>Miniſter</hi> exhort him to take his Sickneſs, and (if it ſhould ſo pleaſe God) his Death too, with patience and ſubmiſſion; it being a Tribute we are all obliged to, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God, when freely paid. He muſt alſo admoniſh him, that if he has any Goods in his poſſeſſion that belong to his Neighbour, he ſhould, if poſſible, make immediate Reſtitution thereof, and not leave it to be done by his Heirs or Executors, who perhaps will forget it as ſoon as he is dead.</p>
               <p>What we have here ſaid of <hi>Reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> is to be underſtood of things that are undoubtedly another Man's, or Debts that he has legally contracted, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of no diſpute. But if it be a doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Debt, and the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> be able to give a clear account of it, he muſt by all means be advis'd to do it, in order to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99316:18"/> the reſtoring what is not his own: Or if he cannot preſently clear the Matter, as may happen in the Caſe of a Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian to a Minor, or a Steward or Agent to One of a great Eſtate or Dealings; he muſt be told, that he ought by a ſpecial Clauſe in his Laſt Will and Teſtament, to oblige his Heirs, Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, or Adminiſtrators, under a certain penalty to prepare immediately after his Death, the Accounts he ſhould have given-in himſelf, had he lived; and what ſhall be found to be remaining due, to pay without delay. And if he ow'd a clear Sum, which he was not then in a condition to pay, he ought likewiſe to oblige his ſaid Adminiſtrators to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge it as ſoon as may be. But if it were at all poſſible, 'twould be much better and ſafer for him to make all thoſe Reſtitutions himſelf, before his Death, than to charge them that come after him therewith.</p>
               <p>Again, if the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> be publickly known to have been at Enmity with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one, he ought not only to be now in Charity with him, but (if poſſible) ſee him; and as his Hatred has made a noiſe in the World, ſo it would not be amiſs that his Reconciliation were made
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99316:18"/> before Witneſſes, to remove the Scandal occaſioned thereby. And if it was he that gave the firſt offence to his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, he ought to ſend to him to beg his Pardon for his misbehaviour, and make him ſatisfaction for the Wrong he may have done him. This is meant of publick Injuries. But if it be a private Grudge or Spleen, Prudence requires, That Satisfaction ſhould be made in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, and only with the Perſons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd therein.</p>
               <p>And if he is under an Obligation of repairing the Honour and Reputation, which by Slander he may have taken away from his Neighbour, let him do it in the beſt manner he can, either by himſelf or another, by word of Mouth, or in Writing. And Laſtly, If he has had the misfortune to incur the Publick Cenſure of the Church, he ſhould be exhorted to an humble ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and acknowledgment of his Crime.</p>
               <p>This being over, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhall more particularly diſpoſe him to receive the <hi>Holy Sacrament</hi> of the <hi>Lord's Supper;</hi> preparing him thereto by Acts of Faith, Hope, and Charity, and above all a profound Humility before God; who
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99316:19"/> has ſaid, by his Prophet, <hi>That he dwelleth with him that is of a contrite and humble Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Advice to be given to a <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> concerning his <hi>Relations,</hi> his <hi>Body,</hi> and his <hi>Eſtate.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE <hi>Miniſter</hi> having done with the Patient, in whatever he thought neceſſary for the good of his Soul, he muſt now proceed to the adviſing him to think of his <hi>Relations;</hi> to declare where he will be Buried; and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of his Worldly Goods: Of which he might have put him in mind before he adminiſtred the <hi>Holy Sacrament</hi> to him. But if he omitted it then, he ought now to do it; and firſt of all, to offer to him, the conſideration of his Wiſe and Children, eſpecially if the latter be under Age; that he may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point an honeſt and careful Perſon for their Guardian, whom he can truſt with their Education and Eſtate. And in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99316:19"/> caſe he has any Daughters not yet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd of, that he may leave them (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Ability) wherewith to live, either a Single or Married Life, as it ſhall pleaſe God to order it.</p>
               <p>And if he has Nephews or other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations under his Care, or Servants he owes any Wages to, or is in conſcience oblig'd to provide for, that he be not remiſs in his Juſtice and Charity to every of them.</p>
               <p>In like manner, if the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> has had the Management and Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any one's Eſtate or Affairs, or has been in any Publick Employment, or concerned in any part of the King's Service; let the <hi>Miniſter</hi> exhort him, ſtrictly to examine his Conduct and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour with relation thereto, that if he finds any thing, reſpecting the diſcharge of ſuch his Duty or Truſt, that troubles his Conſcience, he may tell it him; or cauſe it. to be told by ſome body elſe, to the Parties concerned.</p>
               <p>He ſhould be ask'd alſo, what Place he deſires to be Buried in; in caſe he has not yet declared it. But above all, ſhould be deſired to prohibit any ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous Pomp at his Funeral, which does not in the leaſt contribute to the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99316:20"/> of the Soul; but is commonly done by the Friends and Relations, out of Pride and Vain-glory: Shewing him, that a good Chriſtian ought to direct and enjoyn, that his Burial be made in an humble and modeſt, and decent manner and at moſt but ſuitable to his Quality and Condition.</p>
               <p>In the making his Will and diſpoſing of his Eſtate, let the <hi>Miniſter</hi> exhor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him, carefully to avoid all unjuſt Partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities; which are often-times very ill grounded: Or if he has made his Will already, 'tis fit he be ask'd whether he has any thing to add to, take from, or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in it: which may be done by a <hi>Codici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> annext; putting him in mind to order therein, the payment of his Domeſticks Wages, and what other Debts he owes.</p>
               <p>If his Eſtate be ſo conſiderable as to admit of Pious Legacies, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> may ſhew him the Order he ought to obſerve herein. And much better and ſafer it would be for him to ſee the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution of his own Charities before he dies, than to charge his Heirs or Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrators with them; it too often fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, that they prove very hard and backward in the acquitting themſelves
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99316:20"/> therein: Whereas, if he ſaw the ſame done in his Life-time, the Poor would reap the greater benefit, and himſelf the more ſatisfaction from it; and he might ſay with St. <hi>Lawrence, The hands of the Needy have carried up my Alms to Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if among his pious Legacies, he deſigns to found an <hi>Hoſpital</hi> or <hi>Almſhouſe,</hi> or ought of this kind, that may remain a Monument to Poſterity, let him take great care, that he does it not, more out of Pride and a Vain-glorious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of being celebrated for his Munificence, than through a ſincere Love to God; making him ſenſible, that thoſe Foundations that are laid purely for Charity-ſake, and the Service of God, and true Religion, are infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more pleaſing and acceptable to Him, than the beſtowing of a Man's whole Eſtate upon the Poor, with any other proſpect or intention. Upon which the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhall adviſe him to make a ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous reflection; and to take notice alſo, that though the Foundation of <hi>Hoſpitals</hi> and other Places of Charity, be a very commendable Work; yet the neceſſities of the Poor may at that juncture be ſo great, as to render his Alms much better
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99316:21"/> and more effectually imploy'd, in ſome Bequeſt of preſent Relief to them.</p>
               <p>As the <hi>Miniſter</hi> himſelf ought not to be in the leaſt byaſs'd by a Spirit of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, ſo will it be very adviſable for him, to retire whilſt the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> is making his Will, leaſt he ſeem by his preſence to beg ſomething for himſelf. Let him only (if the Teſtator ſo deſires) give him his Advice, as in the preſence of God, and then withdraw; always remembring that his Function is an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Charity, and ought to be remote from all Self-intereſt.</p>
               <p>If the Teſtator be determin'd to leave his pious Legacies at large, and without reſpect to any particular Perſons; in this Caſe the Miniſter may point him to ſuch, whether of his own or other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, as he know to be Worthy Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of his Charities, and eſpecially thoſe that are aſham'd to beg: As alſo to the redeeming Slaves out of Captivity; the marrying of poor Maids, that might otherwiſe go aſtray; the providing for poor Orphans, and putting them out to Apprentiſhip; the relieving of Priſoners for Debts (incurr'd by their misfortunes,) or any other Perſons that groan under known Wants and Diſtreſſes. In which
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99316:21"/> Diſpoſal and Ordering of Charities, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard muſt be had both to the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Place and Time, and the Perſon giving, and Things to be given: For Example, if the <hi>Patient</hi> be a <hi>Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> eſpecially if he has any Cure of Souls, as a Biſhop or Curate, he ſhould be advis'd to prefer in his Charities, the Poor of his own Dioceſs or Pariſh.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Let no Advice be wanting, towards enabling the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> to make choice of fit and honeſt Men for the Executors of his <hi>Laſt Will</hi> and <hi>Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> ſuch as he has by experience known to be his Faithful Friends, and may repoſe a particular Confidence in, for their maintaining the Intereſt of his Family.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:99316:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> What the <hi>Miniſter</hi>'s Duty is, when he finds the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> has not done all that is neceſſary for him, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to his dying as a good <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> has expreſs'd a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere ſorrow for his Sins, and has not yet receiv'd the Sacred <hi>Viaticum,</hi> the <hi>Miniſter</hi> is to exhort him forthwith to receive it; that out of this Fountain of Holineſs he may draw ſuch Strength and Comfort, as may enable him pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently to bear the pains of his Diſtemper: And to the end he may be put into a better State of appearing in God's Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, let the <hi>Miniſter</hi> endeavour to raiſe in him an ardent deſire and appetite for this Holy Sacrament, by putting him in mind of what happen'd to <hi>Elijah;</hi> who, as he was flying from <hi>Jezebel,</hi> and imploring of God, that Death might put an end to his Afflictions, had no ſooner eaten the <hi>Bread,</hi> and drunk the <hi>Cup</hi> of <hi>Water,</hi> which the Angel ſet before him, but through the ſtrength of that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99316:22"/> Divine Food, found himſelf enabled to march Fourty Days and Fourty Nights, till he came to <hi>Horeb,</hi> the Mount of God, whither he betook himſelf for Refuge. This Example of the Prophet ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent to him, as by a Figure, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Strength, which the <hi>Holy Euchariſt</hi> communicates to a <hi>Dying Chriſtian,</hi> deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of Salvation; it being alſo to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated to him, that there is no time to be loſt herein, leſt by delay ſomething ſhould happen to prevent his receiving this Divine Comfort. Let the <hi>Miniſter</hi> therefore endeavour to prepare him, as we have ſaid in the Second Chapter, by all the Arguments he ſhall judge neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and proper for that purpoſe; and if he finds in the <hi>Patient,</hi> a deſire of Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation with his offended Neighbour, he may ask him, whether he has forgot or omitted to disburthen himſelf of ought that troubles his Conſcience; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he thinks he has any thing reſting in his hands of another Man's Goods; whether he has ſlander'd any one; or has not ſincerely reconcil'd himſelf to his Enemy: And then let the <hi>Miniſter</hi> apply himſelf to the weighing of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, and conſidering from them, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be truly and throughly penitent;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99316:23"/> and in caſe he finds him not altogether ſo much ſo as he ought to be, his next care ſhould be, to raiſe in his heart a true Sorrow and Contrition for his Sins, by all the Means we have ſet down in the fore-mention'd Chapter.</p>
               <p>If the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> has not yet made his <hi>Laſt Will</hi> and <hi>Teſtament,</hi> he may be adviſed to make it now without delay, leſt ſome accident or other happening in his Malady, ſhould render him incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of doing it hereafter. But if he has done it, and the <hi>Miniſter</hi> is appriſed, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by what he ſays, or by the Report of ſome other Perſons of Credit and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, that he is not throughly ſatisfied with it, let him direct the <hi>Patient</hi> to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in a <hi>Codicil</hi> (as we have ſaid ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where elſe) whatever he deſires ſhould be either further, or otherwiſe executed after his Death. And without occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too great a terror to him, let him make him ſenſible of his approaching Diſſolution, and all the while entertain him in the Acts of Faith, Hope, and Charity; aſſuring him, as much as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, of his Salvation, by the Means we ſhall mention in the following Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:99316:23"/>
               <p>But if the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> be likely to live for ſome time yet, and alſo has his Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes perfect, let ſome Godly Book or other be read to him; chooſing above all, that which he us'd himſelf to read, and draw Comfort from, whilſt he was in health. And if the <hi>Miniſter</hi> diſcovers, that he has not enough reflected upon his Sins, and has left ſome unrepented of, he ſhall repeat and explain to him God's <hi>Commandments,</hi> to the end he may put him in mind of his Breaches of them, and ſhew him the neceſſity of his particular Repentance for every Tranſgreſſion he has been guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of.</p>
               <p>Let the <hi>Miniſter</hi> take ſpecial care, that he does not too much entertain him with the Expectation of Life: For it may ſo happen, that flattering himſelf with theſe hopes, he may be apt to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect thoſe Things that are moſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to his Eternal Salvation. In ſhort, if after his Receiving the Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and all that has been ſaid to him, he ſtill remains diſquieted in his Mind, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhould ask him, whether he has any thing more to diſcover. And if he finds this diſquiet of his to ariſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from Scruples, or the Fear of God's Judgments, he ſhall do whatever in him
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99316:24"/> lies to calm his Conſcience, and bring Peace to his Soul, in the manner that ſhall be ſhewn hereafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> How <hi>Sick Perſons,</hi> eſpecially ſuch as are not very perfect in their <hi>Belief,</hi> ought to be exercis'd in the <hi>Faith.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE <hi>Miniſter</hi> finding the <hi>Sick Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> though believing all the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of our <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi> yet not ſo clear and perfect in that <hi>Belief</hi> as he ought to be, ſhall inſtruct him therein in few words, and in a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod ſuitable to his Capacity: As for Example; by rehearſing the <hi>Apoſtles Creed</hi> in conjunction with him, and giving him an Explanation of its Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents. From which if the <hi>Patient</hi> ſhall think himſelf in ſome meaſure inlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened, but not yet ſufficiently acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſome certain <hi>Articles</hi> thereof, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> may prudently and dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly inſtruct him concerning the ſame, without any ſhew of catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99316:24"/> of him, but by way of Prayer exhorting him to ſay after him. <hi>Lord! I commend my Soul to Thee. O moſt Holy, Bleſſed and Glorious Trinity, Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, One only God in Three Perſons and Unity of Subſtance, have mercy upon me. I commit my ſelf to Thee, O Father Almighty, who haſt created Heaven and Earth, and all things viſible and inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. I commend my ſelf to Thee, O Bleſſed</hi> JESU, <hi>Saviour of my Soul, who waſt ſent from Heaven by the Father Eternal; Who waſt conceived by the Operation of the Holy Ghoſt in the Womb of the Virgin</hi> MARY; <hi>Who Suffer'dst, Dyedſt, and waſt Buried; Who didſt deſcend into Hell, and roſeſt again on the Third Day; Who aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendedſt into Heaven, and art ſitting on the right Hand of God the Father Almighty: From whence Thou ſhalt come to Judge all Men, who are to riſe again in their own Bodies; giving Life to ſuch of them as ſhall have dyed in Grace, and adjudging the</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates <hi>to Eternal Fire. I commend my ſelf to Thee,</hi> Holy Spirit, <hi>who proceedeſt both from the</hi> Father <hi>and the</hi> Son, <hi>and whom, together with theſe Two</hi> Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>I adore with one and the ſame Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; who inliveneſt and ſanctifieſt One Catholick and Apoſtolick Church on Earth,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99316:25"/> in which Thou haſt ordain'd Two Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for the Remiſſion of Sins and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Thy Self: I beſeech Thee, I humbly intreat Thee, through Thine Own Merits, O ſweet</hi> JESU, <hi>my</hi> Redeemer, <hi>by Thy tender Love and Mercy, and by all that Thou haſt done and ſuffered for me, to lead me to thoſe Manſions of Eternal Bliſs and Glory, which Thou haſt prepar'd for thoſe that love Thee.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>The ſame thing may be done alſo by way of Oblation; as, <hi>I Offer up my Heart and my Soul to Thee, O Lord, who,</hi> &amp;c. Or by way of Supplication; as, <hi>Have mercy upon me, O Lord,</hi> &amp;c. Or Laſtly, by way of Thanſgiving; as, <hi>I thank Thee, O moſt Holy, Bleſſed, and Glorious Trinity, Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, One only God in Three Perſons, who haſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> &amp;c. as before.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Miniſter</hi> may alſo inſtruct the <hi>Patient,</hi> by raiſing his Hope towards God, and ſhewing him what Father he has by Creation, and at the ſame time explaining to him thoſe Articles of Faith that reſpect the <hi>Divinity:</hi> Then by ſhewing him who his Redeemer is, and acquainting him with the Myſtery of the Incarnation: And laſtly, by tell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him who is his Comforter; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:99316:25"/> to him of the Holy Spirit, and of the Graces which he communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates to us.</p>
               <p>In like manner may he teach him the Articles of his <hi>Belief,</hi> by cauſing him to ponder the Benefits and Favours God has done him; by repreſenting to him, that the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt have created all Things for him; and that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who is the Word, equal to his Father, has been willing to put on Human Fleſh, in order to his Redemption from Sin and Death, and the purchaſing for him a Crown of Everlaſting Glory.</p>
               <p>All theſe different Ways of explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Articles of the <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi> to One that is not throughly acquainted with them, may alſo be very uſeful to thoſe that are the moſt perfect there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; not for inſtructing, but inciting them to Acts of Faith, eſpecially when drawing near to Death; it being very neceſſary at that juncture, to fix in the <hi>Patient</hi> a Belief of thoſe Bleſſings he hopes to enjoy to all Eternity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:99316:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> How the <hi>Miniſter</hi> is to raiſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe the <hi>Hope</hi> of the <hi>Sick Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIRST of all he muſt examine how his Soul is affected; there being three ſorts of Diſpoſitions to be found in <hi>Sick Perſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some have little <hi>Hope</hi> with much <hi>Fear,</hi> whether proceeding from a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Timorouſneſs and the remembrance of their Sins, that perhaps are very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and heinous; or from the Craft and Malice of the Devil, who having pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to them, while they were in health, God's Mercy alone, abſtracted from his Juſtice, for the more eaſie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing them to a Security in Sinning; does, now they are approaching Death and Judgment, preſent to their Eyes the Severity of God's Juſtice unattended with his Mercy; to the end he may caſt them into Deſpair concerning their Salvation, and ſo harden them to a tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough impenitence.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:99316:26"/>
               <p>Others there are; who, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, exceed in <hi>Hope,</hi> even to <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption;</hi> as thinking of nothing but the Virtuous Actions and good Works they fancy to have done, and regarding only the Divine Mercy and infinite Merits of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> without reflecting at all upon their Sins, or the Judgments denounced by God againſt them.</p>
               <p>The third and laſt ſort are ſuch as have neither <hi>Hope</hi> nor <hi>Deſpair;</hi> in whom it is therefore expedient to excite the former, by the Means we ſhall next endeavour to ſhew; referring it to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place to ſpeak of raiſing the Hope of the Timerous, and moderating that of the Preſumptuous.</p>
               <p>As the principal Object of Hope is God, He being the Author of that Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity we look for; ſo there are two Things which the <hi>Miniſter</hi> is chiefly to attend to, with regard to this Head. The one is, the raiſing and fixing the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi>'s Hope upon the Glory Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. The other is, the exciting him to a Chriſtian Confidence that he ſhall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to it.</p>
               <p>He may raiſe his Hope and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en his Courage, by telling him, that within a little time, the Torments and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:99316:27"/> Afflictions which always accompany this preſent Life, will be at an end. He may comfort him alſo with that which made the Prophet rejoyce; namely, <hi>The glad Tidings of his being now going to the Houſe of God;</hi> Wherein he ſhall feel no more Pains, nor Cares, nor Grief; the ſame Prophet aſſuring us, that no Harms, no Sufferings, no Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, no Fears, ſhall ever come nigh the Everlaſting Manſions: Where alſo (as St. <hi>John</hi> ſays) <hi>God ſhall wipe away all Tears from our Eyes.</hi> The <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhall endeavour to lift up his Heart and Mind to the Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that Divine City and ſure Refuge from all our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; where the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil ſhall no longer be able to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue after us; and where we ſhall reap the Eternal Fruits of our Victories over them, and be Crowned with immortal Life and Glory. It may inſpire the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> with ſome ſort of Joy too, to put him in mind, that he will ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly return his acceptable Thanks to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, for his having led him, as it were, through Fire and Water, into a Place of true Refreſhment and Delight. Let him repeat ſometimes the Words which God ſpake by his Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:99316:27"/> Behold, I will extend Peace to them like a River, and Glory like a flowing stream; that is, I will cauſe their hearts to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow with joy and tranquility.</hi> Let him remember with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that God's Children have no abiding and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing City upon Earth; but ought to long for the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> which is above. Let him cry out with <hi>David, O how a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable are thy Tabernacles, Thou Lord of Hoſts! My Soul longeth, yea even fainteth for Thy Courts, O Lord! For there to dwell but one day, or be a Door-keeper in Thy Houſe, is far better and more pleaſant to me, than were I to live Thouſands and ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Years in the Palaces of Worldly Men.</hi> Let him poſſeſs his mind with the unſpeakable Joy he will feel in the Company of ſo many Saints and Bleſſed Spirits, that do, and ſhall ever, love each other with a moſt perfect Love; that reſemble ſo many glorious Kings, who reign, not as the Kings of the Earth, for a little while, and that too in continual troubles and diſquiets; but in the Kingdom of the Living, where there are none but the Children of God, and where Sorrow and Death ſhall never come.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:99316:28"/>
               <p>Let care be uſed to remove from his Soul, all ſort of reluctance or difficulty he may conceive, of parting with his Body; by making him ſenſible, that at preſent 'tis nothing but Filth, and Corruption, and Weakneſs, and Infirmity; and in lieu thereof, will riſe again all Glorious, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, and Immortal. Let him be put in mind of what is intimated to us in <hi>Exodus, That Man ſhall never ſee God, ſo long as he lives in the Fleſh.</hi> For, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith, <hi>God inhabits an inacceſſible Light:</hi> That therefore out of this World we muſt get, before we can enjoy that Glory, ſo ſull of Beauty and Sweetneſs, the ſole fruition whereof makes up the Felicity of the Bleſſed: For which rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it is, that Life Eternal is ſaid in the Goſpel, to conſiſt only in the full Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and Love of God: A Bliſs ſo great, as no Eye ever ſaw, no Ear ever heard, nor has it enter'd into the heart of Man to conceive. Such is to be the Felicity of the Elect; <hi>Who,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>ſhall be ſatisfied and refreſhed with thoſe Rivers of Pleaſure that continually flow from God, as the Well of Life.</hi> Let him be exhorted to ſay with the ſame Royal Prophet, <hi>Like as the Hart deſires the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-brooks, ſo longeth my Soul after Thee, O
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:99316:28"/> God! My Soul is a-thirſt for God, yea even for the Living God. O when ſhall I come to appear before the preſence of God?</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Muſt my Confinement continue yet longer? And ſhall my Soul never be diſſolv'd from this Body, that ſhe may for ever abide with Chriſt my Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our?</q>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe or the like Sentences, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his diſcretion, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhall make uſe of; uttering them in ſuch a manner, as the <hi>Patient</hi> may diſtinctly hear them, and (if he can) repeat them after him, in order to their making the greater impreſſion upon his mind. Thus far of the Means for raiſing his Hope.</p>
               <p>Now for the exciting his Confidence and Aſſurance of obtaining the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs he is labouring after, the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> may uſe theſe three ſeveral ways.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> By moving him to the Exerciſe and Performance of thoſe good Works and Virtues, his Condition ſhall leave him ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of; ſuch as Alms, and pious Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies: Wherein he muſt yet be very cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, how he prompts his Zeal ſo far, as to give any juſt occaſion of murmur or diſſatisfaction to his Friends and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:99316:29"/> But let him not ſpare exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him in all the inward Acts of Faith, Hope, Charity, and Contrition; which no Doubt, will give him great Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, eſpecially if he be fervent and continue in the practice thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> By Conſideration; that is, fixing his Thoughts upon thoſe things he ſhall ſay to him, in order to his ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining this Confidence. And here he may entertain him after this manner. <q rend="margQuotes">Though the Glory of God infinitely exceeds your poor Merits; yet fear you not: God in his Mercy will ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply your Defects, and ſupport your Weakneſs, and comfort your Heart. Be fully perſwaded, that he to whom Grace and Glory belong, will beſtow them on you; inaſmuch as he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely Good, and is pleaſed to make you, and all ſincere Believers, happy. You are his Son, and He your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and a Father full of Love and Tenderneſs; who is far more deſirous to receive you into Heaven, than your ſelf can be to obtain it. Why ſhould you therefore at all doubt of your being now going to poſſeſs Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Joy and Felicity? For that alone
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:99316:29"/> it was, He created you: Nor came <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> to die upon the Croſs for any other End, than to open to us the Gates of Heaven, which the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience of our Firſt Parents had ſhut upon us. He has alſo waſh'd in his Precious Blood the Sins you have committed. He has given you his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and preventing Grace that hath wrought Contrition in your heart, ſo as to make you Heir of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Conſider that He who ſo often ſought for you, during the whole Courſe of your Life, even whilſt you deſpiſed and highly provoked him, will ſhew ſo much the more Mercy and Favour to you now, that you humbly proſtrate your ſelf before Him, with a truly broken and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite heart.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Again, The <hi>Miniſter</hi> may comfort the <hi>Sick Perſon,</hi> and more and more eſtabliſh his Truſt and Confidence in God's Mercy, by continuing to ſpeak to him in this ſort. <q rend="margQuotes">Dear Brother, look-up chearfully towards <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and never grow weary of thinking of what he did and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd for your ſake, for the ſpace of Three and Thirty Years He lived
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:99316:30"/> here upon Earth: Who, though ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry God and King of Glory, was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſubject himſelf to pains and contempt, and at laſt, to a ſhameful Death upon the Croſs, for your Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. Be you perſwaded, that ſo many Sufferings will not be loſt, but will certainly procure you Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reſt and Glory. This All-mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful God, who for your ſake was pleas'd to take Human Fleſh upon Him, and hath left a ſenſible Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial of that his infinite Love to you in the Bleſſed Euchariſt; In a word, who has adopted you to be Partaker of his Kingdom; How can he now deny or reject you, ſeeing you ſo well diſpos'd to receive the Impreſſions of his Holy Spirit, and ſo patiently ſubmitting to all the Afflictions where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with He thinks fit to try your Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity?</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Conſider that He is your Advocate and Interceſſor with the Father, and is prevailing with Him at this very time I am ſpeaking to you, for the Pardon of your Sins: Apply your ſelf to Him, and ſay; <hi>O Holy</hi> JESU, <hi>my Redeemer, accept, I beſeech Thee, my Love and my Repentance; Waſh all my Sins
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:99316:30"/> in thy moſt precious Blood; Cover my Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſes and Imperfections with thy Merits and Righteouſneſs; and thus adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed preſent me unto God the Father, that ſo I may be acceptable to Him, for Thy ſake and through Thy Dear Self, O my Sweet</hi> Saviour!</q> All theſe things may be uſeful likewiſe to raiſe a true Chriſtian Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in them, who are afraid of Death: Of whom we have promiſed to ſpeak by and by.</p>
               <p>Another Means to excite Hope in a <hi>Sick Perſon,</hi> is, by Words or Sentences taken out of the Holy Scripture, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dapted into a Form of Prayer, which the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhall firſt devoutly pronounce, and the <hi>Patient</hi> (if able) repeat after him; ſaying, both with Heart and Mouth, <hi>O Almighty God, and my Eternal Creator, I ſhall ever be troubled in my Mind, until I am perfectly united to Thee. The Number of my Tranſgreſſions, I confeſs, ſhould ſet me far from that happy Union: But Thine infinite Mercy will draw me to Thy ſelf. Remember, Lord! that I am the Work of Thine own Hands; and that through the means of Thy Bleſſed Son</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, <hi>Thou haſt call'd me to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of Thy Kingdom. I acknowledg my unfaithfulneſs to be ſuch as renders me
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:99316:31"/> wholly unworthy ſo great a Favour: But by the Merits of Thine only Son, vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe, I beſeech Thee, to admit me into that Place of Reſt and Bliſs, where I ſhall to all Eternity celebrate the Glory of Thy Name. Be Thou pleaſed, O Father of Mercies, to look upon me, as a miſerable Slave, whom Thou haſt redeem'd with the Sacred Blood of Thy Dear Son, and whoſe Sins Thou haſt puniſh'd and taken ſatisfaction for, by cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Him to die upon the Croſs. O have pity on my Soul, and ſuffer not that ſo much Merit be caſt away upon me. In Thee, O Lord, do I put my truſt, let me never be confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: But deliver me for the ſake of Thy dearly beloved Son</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>who by the Merits of his Death and Paſſion, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come my Righteouſneſs, my Sanctification, and my Redemption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why art thou ſo full of heavineſs, O my Soul, and why art thou ſo diſquieted within me? O put thy truſt in God; for I will yet give him thanks, who is the help of my Countenance and my God. Bleſſed are they, O Lord, that dwell in Thy Houſe; they ſhall be always praiſing Thee. O lead Thou me into that Sacred Place, where I may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn Thee perpetual Thanks for the great Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits Thou haſt beſtow'd upon me. And Thou, O my Saviour,</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>who
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:99316:31"/> didſt undergo the heavy Puniſhment due to my Sins, that I might be capable of Eternal Happineſs, haſt ſaid, that Thou art the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection and the Life, that he who does believe in Thee, ſhall never die; nay, though he was even dead, ſhall live. O my God! I believe in Thee, and hope e're long to enjoy and poſſeſs Thee in the Land of the Living. I will come into Thy Houſe; I will wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in Thy Temple, and confeſs Thy Name. For Thou art the Way, the Life, and the Truth. I have ſet God before mine Eyes, and He is on my right hand, ſo that I ſhall not fall: Wherefore my heart is glad and does rejoyce: My Fleſh alſo ſhall reſt in hope. Thou ſhalt ſhew me the Path of Life. In Thy Preſence is the fulneſs of Joy, and at Thy right Hand there is Pleaſure for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhall alſo cauſe the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> to mix Contrition with his Hope, crying-out with <hi>David, Have mercy upon me O God, after Thy great goodneſs; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the multitude of Thy Mercies do away mine Offences. Waſh me throughly from my Wickedneſs, and cleanſe me from my Sin. For I acknowledge my faults, and my Sin is ever before me. Againſt Thee on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have I ſinned, and done ill in Thy ſight. Turn Thy Face from my Sins, and put out
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:99316:32"/> my my Miſdeeds. Make me a clean heart, O God, and renew a right ſpirit within me. Caſt me not away from thy preſence, and take not thy Holy Spirit from me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In a word; let not his Hope of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don be any ways confin'd, but let it be extended to all his paſt Sins; whether Sins of Commiſſion, or Sins of Omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; whether actual Offences againſt God and his Neighbour, or neglect of his Duty towards both. To which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the following Ejaculations may be us'd. <hi>O Bleſſed</hi> JESU, <hi>my only Helper and Amender, repair that good which I have ſo unworthily deſtroy'd in my ſelf, by the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe I have made of thy Graces to me, as well as the ſcandal I have given my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, by my ill Example, Words, and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Supply the imperfections and unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableneſs of my Life, which with grief I confeſs to have ſpent in coldneſs towards Thee, and indifference for my own Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Thou canſt, O Lord, if Thou wilt, even in the little time that I have now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining, reſtore to me all that I have loſt. Supply my wants, and ſtrengthen the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and infirmitys of my Soul. Of all the Actions of my Life there is not one, how pure ſoever it may appear, but has been at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with many defects; nor have I the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:99316:32"/> leaſt merit of my own. But I fly to Thee, O my Saviour; beſeeching Thee to ſupport me with the abundance of Thy Grace; to apply the Merits of Thy Sufferings to my Soul, and preſent her to thy Father, all covered with that moſt precious Blood Thou haſt ſhed for her, ſo as ſhe may find Mercy with Him, and be admitted into his Kingdom of Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Miniſter</hi> having thus eſtabliſhed him in the Hope he ought to have, of obtaining the forgiveneſs of all his Sins, he may (if he finds him able to bear it) ſtill continue the exerciſing of him in pious Thoughts and Ejaculations; requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him to ſay after him with an atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive mind, <hi>O Father of Mercy and God of all Comfort, be favorable to me, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the numberleſs Errors, and Wickedneſſes, and extravagancies of my Life; who like the Prodigal Son, whom Thou haſt propos'd to me as an Inſtance of Thy Fatherly Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, have waſted and abus'd, not only the Temporal, but Spiritual Talents which Thou hadſt committed to my improvement. O my gracious God, I humbly beſeech Thee for the Lord</hi> Jeſus Chriſt'<hi>s ſake, and by the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of his Death and Paſſion, forgive me all my Sins, and remit the Puniſhment due to me for them.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:99316:33"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Lord</hi> JESU, <hi>to whom all Power and Authority belongs. Thou haſt promis'd that thoſe who forgive the injuries done to them, Thou wilt alſo forgive: I do heartily forgive every one that has offended me. Vouchſafe therefore to forgive me all my Wickedneſſes, Ingratitudes, and Infirmities; and let thy Death make atonement for whatever I have done amiſs; to the end, that when my Soul ſhall be ſeparated from this Earthly Body, ſhe may preſently be united to Thee, and made Partaker of Thy Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Miniſter</hi> may alſo (if he judges it convenient) expreſs himſelf in other words; remembring eſpecially, to put the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> often in mind, of the great Love of Chriſt towards him, and of the unſpeakable Sufferings He has un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone to make Satisfaction for his Sins; that the remembrance thereof may encreaſe his Hope, and excite him to Acts of Faith, Charity, and Contrition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:99316:33"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> The Means for exciting <hi>Charity</hi> in a <hi>Sick Perſon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AS Charity</hi> is of all Virtues the moſt excellent, and the greateſt of all Spiritual Gifts; ſo the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ought, as much as in him lies, to entertain the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> in this Divine Love, and by repeated acts to root it in his heart; it being the beſt Diſpoſition he can die in, in order to his perfect enjoyment of God after his Diſſolution.</p>
               <p>And Firſt, For the bringing him du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to conſider how much God deſerves our Love, let him make uſe of ſuch Words as theſe; <q rend="margQuotes">Thou knoweſt, Dear Brother, that the Sum of all the Evangelical Law is, That we ſhould love God with all our Hearts, with all our Souls, with all our Minds, and with all our Strength; and this not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with regard to our ſelves, becauſe it is neceſſary and profitable for us, and without which we cannot be happy; but alſo with reſpect to Him, and his Divine Attributes; who being tranſcendently Good, and Wiſe, and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:99316:34"/> Almighty, and Gracious, and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful, and poſſeſſing all Perfections, above utterance or Conception, it ought to be our great deſire, that all Men ſhould acknowledge Him for ſuch, and pay Him the Honour, Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and Love due to ſo Supream a Being: Who by his Own Nature, and as the Fountain of all Goodneſs, poſſeſſes the Virtues of the Saints and Angels, and of all other Creatures, Viſible and Inviſible; their greateſt Perfections, how admirable ſoever they may appear to us, being at the beſt but faint glimpſes and reflections of his immenſe Light and Glory. And thus you ſee, how much we are bound to love God for his own ſake; whom to behold, is alone ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to make both Angels and Men happy.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Let the <hi>Miniſter</hi> alſo obſerve to him, that God has even prevented us by his Love; and a greater Love, than ever Father bore towards Son, than ever Friend bore towards Friend, than ever Husband bore towards Wife: And that upon this account it is, He has given Himſelf the three Titles of <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Friend,</hi> and <hi>Husband;</hi> to the end
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:99316:34"/> that by theſe endearing Appellations, which expreſs the greateſt tenderneſs among Men, He might make us ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, how great the Love is He bears to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us. If a King that loves his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, deſerves from them a reciprocal Love, 'tis ſurely very fit and juſt, that though we were even vile enough not to love God for his own ſake, yet at leaſt, out of common gratitude, we ſhould love Him, becauſe He has firſt loved us.</p>
               <p>Moreover, let him be admoniſhed to love God, for the Benefits he has receiv'd at his Hand; and this under a double Conſideration.</p>
               <p n="1">I. With regard to the Order of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: For his Creation and Being; for his Immortal Soul, capable of Eternal Happineſs; for the uſe and preſervation of his Senſes; for the Rank aſſign'd all other Creatures, in ſubſervience to his Aid, Pleaſure, and Convenience. And then let him be put in mind, that 'twas not for any need He had of him, that God had heaped all theſe Benefits upon him, but purely out of an abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant Love and Goodneſs, and for which He expects no return of Profit or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:99316:35"/> but only a mutual and reciprocal Love.</p>
               <p n="2">II. With regard to the Order of Grace; That the Father Everlaſting forbore not to give his own Son, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem him from the Slavery of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and perpetual Torments; That this beloved Son humbled himſelf, even to the Death of the Croſs, to purchaſe Eternal Glory for him; That the Holy Ghoſt has many times been pleas'd to deſcend into his Soul, to purifie it from its Spots and Blemiſhes, and repleniſh it with his Divine Inſpirations; That He it is, that comforts him in his Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that allows him time to prepare himſelf to die as behoves a pious Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and has preſerv'd him from being ſnatch'd away ſuddenly. In ſhort; let the <hi>Miniſter</hi> preſent to his Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Pleaſures which God has provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for him; Pleaſures ſo great and raviſhing, as exceed the power of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Man with Tongue to expreſs, or Thought to conceive: And from all this, leave him to judge, with what fervency and faithfulneſs he ought to love Him.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:99316:35"/>
               <p>Again, The <hi>Miniſter</hi> may encline his heart to the Divine Love, by way of Prayer, cauſing him to repeat after him, ſome Words of the Holy Scripture like theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord, Thou haſt ſaid, that we ought to love Thee with all our Hearts, and with all our Souls. Oh! (if it be thy bleſſed Will) encreaſe in me this Divine Charity. I feel a great deſire of loving Thee; and if in this Life I cannot do it to the degree I wiſh, Lord, grant I may in the Eternal State. For whom have I in Heaven but Thee, and whom upon Earth can I deſire in Compariſon of Thee? Thou art the God of my Life, and my Portion for ever. Grant that I may not only love Thee above all the Creatures in the World, but that I may love nothing but Thee and for Thy ſake; that ſo I may look upon Thee as my only Good, both in this Life, and in that which is to come. O infinite Goodneſs! Who ſhall give me power and strength to love Thee infinitely? When will that bleſſed State come, that Thou alone ſhalt have the ſole poſſeſſion of my Heart? When ſhall I be wholly Thine, who am by ſo many ties and on ſo many accounts, bound to be ſo? O let it come, that bleſſed Time, when
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:99316:36"/> God ſhall poſſeſs me fully and entirely, and when I ſhall be able to offer my ſelf to Him without reſerve!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord, who haſt loved me with an Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Love; Who createdſt me of nothing, who ſavedst me when I was worſe than nothing, and haſt ſo often reſtored to me Thy Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Grace, when I had loſt it by my Sins. If I owe my Soul to Thee ſo many ways; what do I not owe Thee for Thy Self, who art ſo Holy and Merciful? To the reſt of Thy tranſcendent Favours, be pleas'd to add, that of inflaming my Heart, ſo as I may love Thee without bounds or meaſure. O Bleſſed Spirit, who art that immenſe Love proceeding from the Father and the Son; Who vouchſafeſt to fill us with Thy Divine Gifts; Encreaſe, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech Thee every moment the Love I have, and ſhall ever continue to have for Thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, The <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhall engage him to a Love of God, by ſome emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Inſtances of the Great Love of the Saints towards Him; whether from the Lives of the Holy Apoſtles, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Bleſſed Martyrs and Confeſſors of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> raiſing there-from an Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of exciting him to Acts of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, and the acknowledging himſelf
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:99316:36"/> a miſerable Sinner, who, contrary to the Example of thoſe Holy Men, had ſo often abandoned his God and Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, for the ſake of the World and vileſt of its Creatures; directing him at the ſame time, to lift up his heart to the Eternal Father, in theſe Words. <hi>Lord, who haſt prevented me by thy manifold Bleſſings, I own my ſelf, to be that miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sinner, that ungrateful Slave, that Wicked Wretch, who have deſpiſed Thee, even Thee my Creator, and my Father. In the Name and for the ſake of Thy dear Son</hi> Chriſt Jeſus <hi>my Redeemer, I implore Thy Pardon, O Father of Mercy: Waſh away all my Iniquities, and have mercy upon me Thy poor Creature, who am the Work of thy own Hands. Aſſiſt me in this laſt Period of my Life: Comfort thou my ſad and afflicted Soul, and preſerve it from being taken out of Thy Arms by the infernal Spirits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Bleſſed</hi> JESU, <hi>who gaveſt Thy moſt precious Blood for my Sanctification and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, be Thou pleaſed to render it efficacious to me in this my laſt Hour. I acknowledge I have many and many times forfeited the Grace Thou beſtowedſt on me, in my</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, <hi>when I was firſt conſecrated to Thee. But Thy Mercy is far above my Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:99316:37"/> Apply to my Soul the Merits of Thy Death; and let me at this moment of my Departure, feel the gracious Effects of Thy infinite Goodneſs and Power! Me, O Lord! the unworthieſt of Thy Creatures, who with an humble and contrite Heart, and a Soul full of Love to Thee and confidence in Thy Mercy, do in a ready expectation of my ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Diſſolution, cry unto Thee, Lord</hi> JESU, <hi>receive my Spirit.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:99316:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> What the <hi>Miniſter</hi> is to do, when coming to a <hi>Sick Perſon,</hi> he finds every thing already done, neceſsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the diſpoſing him to die as a good <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HItherto we have ſpoken of what the <hi>Miniſter</hi> is to do, for the diſpoſing the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> to die well: But if he finds him to be already well prepar'd; to have receiv'd the Holy Sacrament, and to require only ſome Body with him, to entertain him in thoſe Godly Diſpoſitions; the <hi>Miniſter</hi> having firſt ſatisfied himſelf, that he has ſtill the uſe of his Underſtanding, and is in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to hear what he ſhall ſay, may read to him ſomething out of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and repeat over him the uſual Prayers of the Church: And then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; 1. To the ſupplying what (if ought that is neceſſary) may have been omitted in his Preparation. 2. To the exciting him to further Acts of Faith,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:99316:38"/> Hope, and Charity; and comforting him in his Afflictions and Pains. 3. To the recommending his Soul to God. 4. and Laſtly, To the ſaying ſomething for the Edification of ſuch as are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
               <p>To the Firſt: Having deſired thoſe that ſhall be about the <hi>Patient</hi>'s Bed, to withdraw a little, he ſhall ask him (as we have ſaid at the latter end of the Fourth Chapter) whether he feels a calm in his Conſcience; or whether he be doubtful, and deſirous of further information, in any thing concerning his Salvation: And if he be; the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ought diligently to attend, both to the hearing him and giving him ſatisfaction therein. Or if he ſays no, and yet the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſuſpects the Caſe to be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with him, let him adviſe him to bethink himſelf, whether he has not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got to repent of ſome ſecret Sin; or whether he has not been too reſerv'd in ſome certain Particulars, ſuch as the Reſtitution of the Honour or Goods he may have taken away from his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. Which Reſtitution if he be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally convinc'd he ought to make, let him forthwith do it himſelf, if poſſible; or at leaſt, order it to be done as ſoon as
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:99316:38"/> may be. And in caſe he has not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for it, let him be brought faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to promiſe, that if it ſhould pleaſe God to reſtore him to his health again, he would omit nothing for the giving ſatisfaction to all he is indebted to. In like manner, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> is to inform himſelf, whether he has Children, or had the diſcharging of any Publick Offices, or the like; that ſo, he may ask him proper Queſtions concerning the ſame reſpectively, and avoid what elſe would be leſs uſeful.</p>
               <p>As to the Second Head, namely the Exciting the <hi>Patient</hi> to Acts of Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The <hi>Miniſter</hi> is to conſider the bent of his Mind. For if he be one that is Pious, and accuſtom'd to Divine Meditation, and able to pray and meditate by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, 'twill be convenient that he be let alone for ſometime, without interrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But becauſe his Sickneſs may have brought him low, and there may be cauſe to fear, that by reaſon of the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Mind, as well as that of his Body, he may not be able to ſupport himſelf in his holy Cogitations, the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter</hi> may gently ask him, whether he is not willing to be aſſiſted therein<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> To which if he replyes, that he is devoutly
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:99316:39"/> entertaining himſelf, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhall deſire him to communicate his Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to him, that he may be alſo profited thereby. This is a very uſeful Caution: For by it the <hi>Miniſter</hi> will diſcover, whether there be no deluſion or tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion mixt in his thoughts. And if he finds him, as it often happens, to need a Subject to be given him to meditate upon, he ſhall propoſe to him ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Words of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> as theſe recorded in St. <hi>Mathew</hi>'s Goſpel: <hi>Come unto me all ye that travail and are heavy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laden, and I will give you reſt;</hi> Or ſome others relating to the Myſtery of his Paſſion, and eſpecially ſuch as he may be thought to like beſt, and be moſt edified by; remembring him of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Sufferings upon the Croſs, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Torments, and reproachful Death He underwent for our Sins, whoſe heinouſneſs required ſo ſevere a Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in his Sacred Perſon. By which means he may at once be excited to Contrition, and a neceſſary Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of obtaining Heaven, which the <hi>Redeemer</hi> of the World has thus purchas'd for him with his moſt preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Blood.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:99316:39"/>
               <p>If the <hi>Patient</hi> has not ſtrength ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to meditate by himſelf, and yet has enough of his Senſes remaining, to be able both to hear, and to be affected with the Words of Exhortation; then the <hi>Miniſter</hi> will do well to continue him in the Exerciſe of his Contrition, <hi>Faith, Hope,</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> as we have ſaid in the <hi>2d, 5th, 6th,</hi> and <hi>7th,</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; and having repreſented to him how great and ignominious thoſe Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were which our Bleſſed Saviour endur'd, he ſhall add, that our Sins muſt certainly have been very enormous, to have ſtood in need of ſo extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary a Remedy. Let him (if he be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) ſay, Lord! <hi>Have mercy upon me.</hi> Chriſt, <hi>Have mercy upon me, a poor wretched Sinner. I am ſorry from my heart, that ever I have offended Thee. O for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give me all my iniquities; Encreaſe my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and ſupport it, and ſupply its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects with the Merits of Thy Blood. O Merciful Saviour, be favourable unto my Soul that longeth after Thee, and nothing but Thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for the exciting his Faith, let him call to mind, that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> though of one and the ſame Subſtance with the Father, Co-eternal and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:99316:40"/> with Him in all his Perfections, yet has been willing ſo far to humble himſelf, as even to take our Fleſh upon Him, and die on the Croſs for our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; and then let him adore Him as the <hi>Saviour</hi> and <hi>Redeemer</hi> of the <hi>World.</hi> It will be alſo very proper for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and Edification of his Relations and other Perſons preſent, that he openly declare the Profeſſion of Faith he dies in; ſaying, <hi>I proteſt before Heaven and Earth, that I die in the Catholick and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolick Faith, hoping to be ſaved through the ſole Merits of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>our Lord.</hi> Then he ſhall rehearſe the <hi>Apoſtles Creed,</hi> or (if he cannot himſelf do it) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to follow in heart and mind, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> that ſhall pronounce it for him; who at the ſame time may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe his Hopes of Salvation, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring him of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s great Love to him; by whoſe Sufferings it is, that the Gates of Heaven do now ſtand open ready to receive him; by whoſe Wounds and Torments he is heal'd; and by whoſe Death he ſhall obtain Everlaſting Life and Happineſs. The <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhall alſo repreſent to him, the precious Blood which ran from his <hi>Saviour</hi>'s Feet, Hands, and Head, and from all his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:99316:40"/> Body, even from his Side, that was ſo barbarouſly and inhumanly pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with a Spear. He ſhall likewiſe put him in mind of the Crown of Thorns that was ſet on his Head, out of deriſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and contempt; of the Scourges that cruelly tore his Fleſh, as if He had been a Slave; of the Blows He received up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on His Sacred Face, which were not only painful and dolorous, but full of ignominy and confuſion. All which he ſhall lay before him, in order to the raiſing his Confidence, and perſwading him, that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> did thus ſuffer and humble Himſelf, for no other end but his Redemption; making him ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that God who has done ſo much for him, ſurely will not now abandon him, at a time when he has the greateſt need of his Aſſiſtance; and telling him therefore, that if the Devil inwardly reproaches him, and endeavours to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright him, with the heinouſneſs of his Sins, he muſt boldly anſwer him, <hi>My God, in whom I believe and repoſe my truſt, has by his Blood ſhed on the Croſs, waſh'd them away; and is now at the Right Hand of his Father, making interceſſion for me, and ſhewing Him His Body still cover'd, as it were, with that moſt precious Blood,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:99316:41"/> by which He made full Satisfaction and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement for all my Tranſgreſſions.</hi> And then go on in theſe Words. <hi>My God, I put my truſt in Thee. O ſhut not up the Bowels of Thy tender Mercies from me! Ariſe, O God of my Salvation, and ſcatter abroad all my Enemies. Let them that hate Thee flee before Thee; Even as the ſmoke let them vaniſh away, and melt at Thy Preſence, as Wax melteth before the Fire. But let Thy Servant rejoyce.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In ſhort, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhall again and again exhort him to Charity and a Love of God, by the ſeveral Motives before propos'd; and above all the reſt, by that of the exceeding great Love which the Son of God has ſhewn in dying for us; Whereupon he ſhall cry-out with <hi>David, What reward ſhall I give to the Lord for all the benefits that he has done unto me?</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">I cannot better expreſs my love to Him, than by receiving this his Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation with patience and humility. Moſt ready I am, O Lord, to embrace Death it ſelf, to the end my Soul may be united to Thee for evermore.</q>
               </p>
               <p>In like manner ought he to reſign himſelf into the Hands of God, and commend his Spirit to His Mercy. <hi>To Thee, O Lord, I give up my Soul; for
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:99316:41"/> Thou haſt both created and redeemed it. Thine I am, yea, Thine alone. Therefore Thy Holy Will be done in me, and by me. Be Thou only pleaſed to inlighten mine Eyes, that they may readily diſcover the Snares which the Enemy is laying for me, and never ſuffer them to be ſurpris'd by the ſlumber of Death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If he languiſhes by ſlow degrees, and remains ſenſible in his laſt Agony; the Hiſtory of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Paſſion ſhall be read to him out of the Goſpel, together with ſome Chapters of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles, as the <hi>1ſt</hi> and <hi>2d.</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> the <hi>2d</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> and the two laſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the <hi>Revelation</hi> of St. <hi>John;</hi> chooſing the Places in thoſe Chapters that are proper for a <hi>Dying Perſon,</hi> and paſſing over the reſt. Some <hi>Pſalms</hi> may be alſo recited to him, ſuitable to the occaſion. In a Word, let not the <hi>Miniſter</hi> abandon him one Minute, whilſt he appears to have the leaſt remainder of Senſe. For at this laſt Moment it is, as St. <hi>Gregory</hi> tells us, upon the Nineteenth Chapter of St. <hi>Luke,</hi> that the Devil redoubles his Endeavours to deſtroy us. So that the <hi>Miniſter</hi> continuing his Exhortation to him, may (if he finds him capable thereof) deſire him to purſue his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:99316:42"/> to God, after this manner. <hi>Lord, I believe that Thou art my God and my Redeemer. I humbly beg of Thee the pardon and forgiveneſs of all my Sins. I am exceedingly ſorry for the Commiſſion of them; and wiſh my Sorrow were ſtill greater. If I have omitted any thing that Thou requireſt for my Repentance, Lord, I pray Thee, give me a due ſenſe thereof, and fit me for Thy Self. Supply all my imperfections, and make me ſuch as Thou would'ſt have me to be. Lord, I do for Thy ſake freely forgive whatever wrongs and injuries I have received; and heartily ask forgiveneſs of them whom I have any ways offended. If I have ought that is another's due, I deſire to reſtore it, as far as my Abilities will permit. In Thee, O Lord, I place all my Hope; though I know my ſelf unworthy of the leaſt of Thy Mercies: Thy Sufferings and Thy Blood aſſure me of my Salvation. Both my Life and my Death are in Thy Hands. Do Thou with me as it ſhall ſeem good to Thee. 'Tis ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for me to love and bleſs Thee to all Eternity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> be in a condition of bearing with any more Diſcourſe, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhall go on in the ſame Method of aſſiſting him to lift up his Soul to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:99316:42"/> God; and to that end, make uſe of the Words mention'd in the <hi>5th, 6th,</hi> and <hi>7th,</hi> Chapters of this Book; not omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to admoniſh him to beg of God to accept the Prayers, whether publick or private, put up by the Church or his Friends for him.</p>
               <p>As to the Third Head, Which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects the <hi>Miniſter</hi>'s ſolemn Recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the <hi>Dying Perſon</hi>'s Soul to God, the proper time to go about it is, when he perceives him to be ſtruggling with the Pangs of Death, and juſt upon the point of his Departure. The Form there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is preſcribed by the Church. To which (if he finds the <hi>Patient</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue longer than he expected, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt of any remains of his Senſes) he may add ſuch further Sentences of Scripture as he ſhall judge convenient; like theſe. <hi>O Son of David, have mercy upon me. Haſte Thee to deliver me; make haſte to help me, O Lord.</hi> With how much Sincerity, Zeal and Attention, this laſt Office ought to be performed, I hope no good Chriſtian, much leſs thoſe of the Sacred Function, whoſe more particular Province it is, need to be admoniſh'd.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:99316:43"/>
               <p>As to the Fourth Head, Which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the Edification of thoſe that are preſent, we ſhall treat thereof in the laſt Chapter of this Book.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> What means are to be us'd when the <hi>Patient</hi> does not reſign himſelf, as he ought, to the Will of God, and is afraid of <hi>Death</hi> through a too great <hi>Love</hi> of this <hi>Life.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SOME there are, who afflict them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves too much at the approach of <hi>Death,</hi> through an over-great fondneſs of this <hi>Life;</hi> the grief they conceive of parting with it being ſuch, that they cannot ſubmit themſelves to the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of God, but die much againſt their Wills. Which ill diſpoſition produces in the Heart of a <hi>Sick Perſon,</hi> theſe three diſmal Effects.</p>
               <p n="1">I. That by how much the greater his reluctance is, ſo much the more he is troubled and confounded with the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:99316:43"/> of Death; according to the Son of <hi>Sirach</hi>'s Saying, <hi>O Death how bitter is the remembrance of thee, to a man that liveth at reſt in his poſſeſſions!</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. That by this Reluctance of his, he not only deprives himſelf of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort he would receive from his voluntary Reſignation to Death; but runs a great riſque of offending God.</p>
               <p n="3">III. That he does not prepare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as he ought, for Death; nor can reſolve to think of his Eternal State. And the Condition of ſuch a One, is ſo much the more deplorable, in regard no body dares ſpeak to him of Dying. But on the contrary, they are apt to turn their Diſcourſe upon the hopes of his Recovery, for the ſake of entertaining him in an agreeable idea; though in the end moſt pernicious to him, by reaſon of its diverting him from the thoughts of his Salvation. As therefore they ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Eternal Welfare, let both the <hi>Miniſter</hi> and his Friends take heed, that he be not thus dallied with, when his Condition is become dangerous, but that he be in a prudent manner appriſed of the ſame, to the end he may exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:99316:44"/> the State of his Soul; making him ſenſible, that his Preparation for <hi>Death,</hi> will be no impediment to his Recovery, if it pleaſes God to ſpare him longer in this Life. But if he cannot reſolve to die, let the <hi>Miniſter</hi> endeavour to bring his mind over by <hi>Arguments, Examples,</hi> and <hi>Words</hi> in Form of Ejuculatory Prayers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> By <hi>Arguments;</hi> which the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter</hi> is to ground, as much as he can, on the Holy Scripture; to the end they may be not only in themſelves the ſtronger, but of more Authority and Force with the <hi>Patient.</hi> For Example, he ſhall with St. <hi>Paul</hi> tell him, <hi>That it is appointed for all Men once to die:</hi> That on this condition it is we are born, and wherein no diſtinction is made between Princes and Subjects: That we all die, ſoon or late, and flow like the Waters into the Bowels of the Earth; yea, we are like Water that is ſpilt on the ground, from whence it cannot be gathered up. He ſhall alſo repreſent to him, that though he ſhould recover his Health, he may in a little time relapſe again, and not have the means he now has for his Preparation; That he ought to look
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:99316:44"/> upon himſelf as a Pilgrim travelling through this World, as through ſtrange Regions, in his Way to Heaven, which is his Native Country; That he ſhould conſider the many Tokens God has given him of his Love, and that which he at preſent gives him, in aſſiſting him with his Grace: That God now calls him to Himſelf, in order to the making him happy; and that a longer Life here might be ruinous to him, by the ſnares and inticements of this Sinful World: That Death is not terrible to the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, but meerly a Paſſage to Eternal Glory; <hi>And better is the day of our Death than that of our Birth; foraſmuch as we are born to die, and do only die to live for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever:</hi> In ſhort, That <hi>Chriſt</hi> aſſures us in his <hi>Goſpel,</hi> that whoſoever believes in him ſhall have Everlaſting Life, and that his Death ſhall be but the beginning of his Eternal Happineſs.</p>
               <p>Moreover, let the <hi>Patient</hi> be induced to reflect on the Miſeries of this preſent Life. Let him as much as he is able, call to mind the whole Courſe of his Life from his Infancy to this very moment, and conſider before God, whether he has paſs'd one day of it without afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: That we are to expect here nothing
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:99316:45"/> but Sufferrings; God having ſet us in this World as in a Valley of Tears, to live in a conſtant State of Penitence: That therefore we ought not to be grieved, when God is pleaſed to remove us from the Place of our Exile into our own Country; and far from wiſhing our ſelves Citizens of this World, we ſhould with St. <hi>Paul</hi> remember, that here we have no continuing City, but are to look for one that is to come, which will abide for ever.</p>
               <p>Let him further conſider, that being now under the Goſpel, we ſhould be ſo much the more deſirous to die, becauſe <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> has by his Merits open'd Heaven to us: That Death is both the End of a falſe and periſhable Life, and the Entrance into a Happy and Eternal State; That God is not the God of the Dead, but of the Living; That a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> ought to raiſe himſelf above the things of this World, and ſolely to fix his Thoughts and Hopes upon his <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our;</hi> That this Life is a continual War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare with our Luſts and Paſſions, and Death the welcome End of this War and Beginning of our Reſt; That the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God declares thoſe, and thoſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to be happy, that die in his Grace,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:99316:45"/> becauſe they are going to enjoy an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Peace. In a word, let the <hi>Miniſter</hi> omit nothing that may conduce to the perſwading him, to receive his Death with Submiſſion, making him ſenſible, that how averſe ſoever he be to it, yet die he muſt; and that ſince nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Life nor Death are within his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or diſpoſal, he can never be at reſt, till he ſubmits himſelf with all humility and reſignation, to the Will and Pleaſure of Almighty God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>Miniſter</hi> may perſwade the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> to a willingneſs to die, by laying before him ſeveral Examples of this kind, carrying force and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity with them; and in the firſt place, that of <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf; who in the <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> of <hi>Olives,</hi> foreſeeing the Torments that were waiting for Him at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> was ſeized with fear, and pray'd to the Father, to deliver Him therefrom; but immediately after, ſubmitting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to Him, added theſe Words, <hi>Not as I will, but as Thou wilt.</hi> That he ought to imitate this <hi>Sacred Model</hi> of Self-reſignation, by a free Offering of his Life to God, notwithſtanding the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror he has of <hi>Death,</hi> and all the reluct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances of Nature thereto. Let him alſo
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:99316:46"/> be put in mind of <hi>David,</hi> who finding himſelf over-whelm'd with the Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of this preſent Life, us'd frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to cry out to God in terms like theſe. <hi>Wo is me, that I am conſtrained to dwell with</hi> Meſech, <hi>and to have my Habitation among the Tents of</hi> Kedar. <hi>My ſoul has long dwelt with them that hate peace. Many are my Perſecutors and mine Enemies: Conſider my affliction and deliver me: I long for thy Salvation, O Lord!</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to he may add the words of St. <hi>Paul, O wretched Man that I am! Who ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live me from this body of Death? I ardent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire to be diſſolved, that I may forever live with</hi> Chriſt, <hi>who is my Life.</hi> And theſe of the Wiſe Son of <hi>Sirach; Fear not the Sentence of Death. Remember them that have been before thee, and that come after. For this is the Sentence of the Lord over all fleſh: And why art thou againſt the pleaſure of the moſt High? There is no inquiſition in the grave, whether thou haſt liv'd ten, or an hundred, or a thouſand years.</hi> Let him repreſent to him St. <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larion</hi> ſurpris'd by Thieves, who with Sword in Hand, are juſt going to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther him; when aſtoniſh'd to ſee him ſo unconcern'd, and asking him why he fear'd not Death. <hi>'Tis,</hi> anſwered he,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:99316:46"/> 
                  <hi>becauſe I have been a long time preparing my ſelf for it.</hi> He may alſo obſerve to him the Words of St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> who ſays, <hi>that ſuch only ought to fear</hi> Death, <hi>as lack</hi> Faith, <hi>and have no Hope of reigning with</hi> Chriſt. To all which the <hi>Miniſter</hi> may ſuperad divers Examples and Sayings of other Saints and Martyrs, who have wiſh'd and long'd for their Diſſolution; whereby to pacifie and calm the trouble with which the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi>'s mind is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The laſt means we propos'd for removing the <hi>Patient</hi>'s Fear of Death is, by Ejaculatory Prayers; the <hi>Miniſter</hi> teaching and aſſiſting him to ſay after this manner. <hi>O my God! I feel the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of Death upon me; but as much as in me lies I ſacrifice them to Thee, and am ready to die, if it be thy Pleaſure. I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſubmit my will to Thine. O Lord, who haſt created me, preſerved me, and by a ſpecial Grace cauſed me to be born within thy Church, to the end I might be ſaved: What reward ſhall I give unto Thee for all theſe Benefits? I will receive at Thy Hand this Cup of my Death, which Thou preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to me. I take it, O my God, with all my heart, in teſtimony of my Love and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to Thee. If Thou, O Lord, haſt ſo</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:99316:47"/> 
                  <hi>decreed it, notwithſtanding my natural reluctance thereto, I am moſt ready and willing to die, hoping my Death will, through thine infinite Goodneſs, be follow'd by Eternal Reſt. O Father of Mercy and God of all Comfort, I thank Thee, that I am now come to my laſt hour, which will put an end to all my Sins. I thank Thee eſpecially, that Thou hast been pleas'd to afford me time to prepare my ſelf for Death. O help Thou me in my troubles and anguiſhes: Strengthen my Soul that ſtands ſurrounded with the dangers of Hell. Support my weakneſs, and be my ſtrong Defence againſt Satan; that ſo I may die in Thy Favour and Love. I know that my Redeemer lives, and that he ſhall ſtand at the latter day upon the Earth; And though after my Skin Worms deſtroy this Body, yet in my fleſh will I ſee God: Whom I ſhall ſee for my ſelf, and mine Eyes ſhall behold, and not another. Lord, I beſeech Thee, encreaſe my Faith and Confidence in Thee, and comfort thou me in all my Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus may the <hi>Miniſter</hi> entertain the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> in devout Meditations and Prayers; making uſe alſo, of ſuch other Words and Sentences, as he ſhall judge proper for the raiſing his Soul, and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:99316:47"/> fixing his Thoughts and Deſires upon God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> What is to be ſaid to a <hi>Sick Perſon,</hi> whoſe unwillingneſs to die proceeds from an exceſſive Love for the Things of this World.</head>
               <p>OThers there are, who are very loath to think of <hi>Death;</hi> not ſo much (like thoſe mentioned in the preceding Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) from an over-fondneſs of Life it ſelf, as a difficulty of quitting ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Things and Circumſtances at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending it; ſuch as Riches, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Pleaſures; and above all, the Perſons they moſt dearly love, their Wives and Children, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> On which laſt account, the Poor Man's Caſe claims our greateſt pity and attention: For whilſt his heart is fill'd with grief and anxious thoughts, what will become of his diſtreſſed Family, the Devil ne're fails to lay hold on this Occaſion, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert his Mind from the Buſineſs of his
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:99316:48"/> Salvation. If therefore the <hi>Miniſter</hi> find this to be the Condition of the <hi>Patient;</hi> having firſt exhorted thoſe that are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, humbly to implore Almighty God to allay his Diſquiets, and render his Mind free and compoſed, to the end he may think of nothing but <hi>Eternity;</hi> let him make uſe of the following Means for comforting him.</p>
               <p>And in the Firſt place, let him cauſe all ſuch Perſons to withdraw, whether Wife, or Children, or others, whoſe preſence may attract the <hi>Patient</hi>'s Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to this World, and keep up thoſe melancholy thoughts he is in; taking care to prevent, as much as poſſible, his being ſpoken to about them, further than he ſhall think of abſolute neceſſity, with regard to their future Settlement. After which he may proceed to inform him, that this Diſquiet of his, is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſeleſs both to himſelf and Family, but moſt prejudicial to his Soul; in that it obſtructs its due <hi>Preparation</hi> for <hi>Death;</hi> That the Poverty under which he leaves his Family, is an Evil that ſoon or late will have an end; but the Torments of the other World have none; and that therefore in theſe laſt moments of his Life, he ought to entertain no other
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:99316:48"/> thoughts but how to avoid his own Eternal Miſery: That his Family is under the Conduct of the Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, that loves them, and will watch over them, and beſtow on them Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Goods ſufficient; perhaps too great a meaſure thereof; ſo that inſtead of afflicting himſelf with the Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the ſad Condition he leaves them in, he ought on the contrary, to rejoyce in God, and to lift up his Heart and Mind to Him, and to beg his Grace to forget and reject whatever reſpects not his Everlaſting Salvation; with full perſwaſion, that God, to whom he is to recommend his Wife and Children, (as <hi>Chriſt,</hi> when ready to die, did his Diſciples) will be their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, and Helper, and Defender; who being alſo more their Father than he himſelf is of his own Children, and governing all things both in Heaven and on Earth by his Almighty Providence, will ſupply them with whatſoever is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, as well for their Bodies as their Souls.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">This Truſt and Confidence (the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhall ſay to him) will be more available to the good of your Family, then all the diſquieting
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:99316:49"/> thoughts you can entertain about them. For God is Merciful, and will grant us every thing we ask according to his Will. Moreover, remember, that he who undertakes a long Journey, ſhould not carry ought about him that is comberſom. You are ſetting-out upon your Journey to Eternity, and may within a little time appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Tribunal of God. Take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you therefore no ſuch unneceſſary Burden, as that of the care of your Wife and Children. Peradventure they have been the cauſe of your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting many Sins in the courſe of your Life: Beware they be not that of your undoing now. Disburthen your heart of this heavy Load; that ſo it may be able to raiſe it ſelf up to God, and ſavour nothing but things Eternal. Conſider that both your Life it ſelf, and all the Goods you have enjoy'd in this World, were not yours, but God's, who lent them you only for your uſe, as means of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging your Love to him. And if he takes them away again, you have no reaſon to complain; but your Duty is freely to lay them down; remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> (who is Lord
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:99316:49"/> of all) died upon the Croſs naked and diveſted of all Worldly Deſires. You know that God took from <hi>Job</hi> all that he poſſeſs'd, and yet that Prince ſaid only this, <hi>Naked came I out of my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Womb, and naked ſhall I return thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: The Lord gave, and the Lord has taken away; bleſſed be the Name of the Lord.</hi> Endeavor to be as diſintangled and looſe from the World as that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Perſon was.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Which Exhortations the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhall conclude, with moving the <hi>Patient</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat after him ſome Sententious Prayers, like theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deliver me, O Lord, from all affections for the things of this World, and fix in my heart the ſole deſire of poſſeſſing thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How amiable are thy Dwellings, O Lord of Hoſts!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My ſoul longeth, yea even fainteth for the Courts of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My heart and my fleſh crieth out for the Living God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For one day in thy Courts is better than a thouſand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I had rather be a Door-keeper in the Houſe of my God, than live in the Palaces of Worldly Princes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There ſhall I be ſatisfied, as it were, with
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:99316:50"/> marrow and fatneſs, and ſhall drink of thy Pleaſures as out of the River.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For with Thee is the Well of Life, and in thy preſence is the fulneſs of joy, and at thy right hand there is pleaſure for evermore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereto the <hi>Miniſter</hi> may add, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his diſcretion, what of any of the foregoing Chapters, he ſhall judge neceſſary, for putting the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> into a frame of dying like a good <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus far of thoſe, whoſe Reluctances to Death proceed from a too great Love of this Life, and the Pleaſures and Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions attending it. For ſuch whoſe terrors ariſe only from an imagination, that there may not be time enough re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining for them to explain, as they ought, ſome particular Matters which diſturb their Conſciences. For ſuch, we ſay; till we come to give them more ample Inſtructions in the ſequel of this Diſcourſe, let us in the mean time excite them to be very good Husbands of thoſe Moments which are yet behind, which may not be ſo few as they appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend: Let them employ the ſame in Self-Examination, Prayer, and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; in an immediate Reſtitution of what is not their own; or if that cannot be, in providing by their <hi>Teſtament</hi> or
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:99316:50"/> 
                  <hi>Codicil,</hi> that it be done with all poſſible Expedition; as we have ſaid in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding Chapters. And laſtly, for ſuch as are troubled to die, for this only rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, becauſe they had reſolved to alter their Courſe of Life, and propos'd to themſelves the doing of many pious Works; they muſt be perſwaded to reſign themſelves up to the Will of God; and inſtead of that Good which they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to have done, to offer up their Lives to Him as a Sacrifice, with a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition humbly and readily to receive, whatever it ſhall pleaſe his Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence to determine concerning them: Than which they cannot offer to God any thing greater or more acceptable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:99316:51"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> What is to be done to a <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> that is <hi>Impatient.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IMpatience</hi> in a <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from either of theſe two Cauſes; The languiſhing Condition which the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity of his Diſtemper has reduced him to; Or Poverty, which leaves him deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the Helps and Remedies neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for his Recovery. The Caſe being ſuch, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> is in the firſt place to comfort him, by aſſuring him, how much he is grieved to ſee him in that deplorable Condition, and uſing all the Means he can, to procure him Eaſe and Relief; that ſo he may the more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally perſwade him, of his partaking ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely with him in his affliction. Which charitable manner of proceeding, cannot fail of winning his Heart, and engaging him to hearken with more patience and willingneſs, to whatever ſhall be ſaid to him concerning his Salvation.</p>
               <p>Then let the <hi>Miniſter</hi> repreſent to him, that his Impatience is ſo far from dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing his illneſs, that it does but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:99316:51"/> it, and deprive him of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and Satisfaction he would reap, from the taking this his Viſitation with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and ſubmiſſion; the beſt and moſt effectual Means for rendring thoſe Evils lighter and more ſupportable, which are not within Human power to remove: For, according to the ſaying of St. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome, Tribulations do purſue with much greater vehemence, thoſe that fly from them, than thoſe that receive them without mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring or repining.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, he ſhould be admoniſhed to conſider, That God ſends theſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, only for him to make a good uſe of them, as Helps for his Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: That therefore, inſtead of being grieved and diſpleaſed thereat, he ought to praiſe and thank His Divine Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for them, as being Graces neceſſary to his Eternal Salvation: That upon this account it is, that <hi>Solomon</hi> will not have us to fly from the Chaſtiſements of the Lord, nor grow weary and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient under the troubles He is pleas'd to diſpenſe to us; He correcting only thoſe He loves, and adminiſtring there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by an occaſion to us, of drawing Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation from the very pains which He in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts on us, provided we bear them with
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:99316:52"/> due Meekneſs and Reſignation. Let him reflect on the vaſt Number of Sins he has committed, and the ſevere puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he deſerves for them; The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of which will certainly, if any thing, oblige him with the deepeſt Contrition and humility, to commit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into the Hands of God, and readily embrace whatever troubles or anguiſhes, his Divine Wiſdom ſhall think fit to exerciſe him with, even Death it ſelf, in hopes of appeaſing God's wrath there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, and rendring Him more favourable and gracious to him; Of which the <hi>Miniſter</hi> may give him Confidence: Adding, that Afflictions are only ſent us, to take off our Minds from this World, and raiſe them to the Contemplation of Things Eternal; and that God is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be with the Afflicted, who are of a yielding and ſubmiſſive Spirit; Saying by his Prophet, <hi>I am with him in trouble; I will deliver him, and he ſhall glorifie me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In a word, let him ſeriouſly conſider, that we are viſited with pains and griefs, to try our Virtue, exerciſe our Faith, and encreaſe our Contrition; and that for this Cauſe it is, that the Son of <hi>Sirach</hi> adviſes us to receive all kinds of Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:99316:52"/> with humbleneſs of heart; for as Gold is try'd by the Fire, ſo are Men by the Tribulations of this preſent Life.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, The <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhall repreſent to him, that Heaven is prepared for thoſe that patiently ſuffer in this World; that the Hand of God does by Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, poliſh us (as it were) like Stones, of which He will Build his Heavenly <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem;</hi> and that therefore, in order to our being made happy, we ought ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſively to bear whatever Burthen He pleaſes to lay upon us. Which Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the <hi>Miniſter</hi> may greatly inforce, by inculcating to him the Examples of <hi>Job,</hi> the Holy <hi>Apoſtles, Martyrs,</hi> and <hi>Confeſſors,</hi> and <hi>CHRIST</hi> Himſelf <hi>Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified,</hi> eſpecially by diſplaying to him the exceſſive Torments of the Croſs; and at the ſame time propoſing to his <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> by way of Prayer and Self Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation, theſe Words of St. <hi>Auſtin's; Lord! burn me, cut me into pieces, ſcourge me, and correct me in this World, ſo Thou pardon me in the next:</hi> Or theſe, <hi>O God who chaſtiſeſt thoſe whom Thou do'ſt love, admit me, I beſeech Thee, after my Death, into the Number of Thy Bleſſed Children, ſince Thou makeſt me to endure thy Correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in this Life. My God! and my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther!
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:99316:53"/> Who art my only Refuge and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, ſuccour me in all my Afflictions and Miſeries, either by aſſwaging and moderating them, or giving me ſtrength to ſuſtain the ſame without repining. I thank Thee, O Merciful Father, for the troubles Thou haſt laid upon me. Thou that knoweſt my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, vouchſafe to fortifie and ſupport me; ſo as I may not fall into impatience and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur; but that I may truly humble my ſelf under Thy Afflicting Hand, and wholly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to Thy Chaſtiſements.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which the <hi>Miniſter</hi> may ſtill add, what other Words of the like kind he ſhall judge convenient, with regard to the Condition of the <hi>Sick Perſon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:99316:53"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> How thoſe <hi>Perſons</hi> ought to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged, that lie under <hi>Temptations</hi> againſt the <hi>Faith.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OF <hi>Perſons</hi> tempted againſt the <hi>Faith,</hi> there are two Sorts: Either they are ſuch, as have not a clear apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all that is neceſſary to be believed in the Law of <hi>Grace</hi> (whom how to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct we have ſhewn in the Firſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;) Or they are ſuch, as are tormented by <hi>Satan,</hi> who is continually endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to caſt Doubts into their Minds, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their <hi>Faith</hi> in general, or ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Article of it. The former of which Caſes being (as we have ſaid) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for in the Firſt Chapter, we ſhall here need only to ſpeak to the latter: Which the <hi>Miniſter</hi> perceiving to be the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi>'s, ſhall adviſe him not to diſpute with the <hi>Devil,</hi> whoſe ſole aim is to deſtroy his <hi>Faith, Without which</hi> (as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tells us) <hi>it is impoſſible to pleaſe God;</hi> but humbly to implore the Holy Ghoſt, ſo to inlighten him, as that he may never fall into Infidelity, nor
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:99316:54"/> the Enemy have any advantage over him.</p>
               <p>Let him cry out with the Prophet, <hi>Lord! thou ſeeſt how I am tempted, be thou pleaſed to anſwer for me.</hi> Adding thereto, if occaſion be, what is before mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Fifth Chapter, and making an humble Confeſſion of that <hi>Faith,</hi> which is founded, not upon human Reaſons, but the Eternal Truth. Which will ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure him againſt all the ill ſuggeſtions, wherewith the Devil may labour to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault and diſturb him, and ſet him en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely at liberty to think of thoſe things, that will adminiſter pleaſure and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to him; ſuch as the unſpeakable Joys of Heaven, which he is hoping for, the infinite Love of God towards him, and Spiritual Graces He has confer'd upon him. And for a yet further di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of thoſe Temptations he finds himſelf obnoxious to, it may be conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for him to ſpeak ſometimes to thoſe that are preſent.</p>
               <p>But if notwithſtanding all theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cautions, he ſhall ſtill perceive his <hi>Faith</hi> to be wavering, let him firſt pray to God to help his Unbelief, and then proteſt before Him and all the Standers by, that he reſolves to die in that <hi>Faith</hi> which <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:99316:54"/> Chriſt</hi> is the Author of, and the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs</hi> have ſealed and atteſted by their Blood.</p>
               <p>And here, if the <hi>Patient</hi>'s illneſs will permit it, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> may offer him ſome general Reaſons, to confirm him in the <hi>Chriſtian Faith</hi> and <hi>Religion;</hi> as, that it flows directly from the <hi>Divine Wiſdom;</hi> and is not, like others, grounded only upon Human Arguments, but the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Truth of God himſelf, who has been pleas'd to reveal it to his Church. But at the ſame time, he muſt be very cautious of deſcending to any particular Point, leaſt it ſhould provoke the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> to Diſputation (a thing moſt dangerous on ſuch an occaſion) unleſs he deſires to be inform'd about ſome of the Myſteries of our Religion: Which is to be done too in as few words as may be.</p>
               <p>Let him be ſhewn, that the <hi>Chriſtian Faith</hi> is eſtabliſh'd upon no leſs, than the Teſtimony of the Eternal Father, who ſaid of <hi>Chriſt, He is my beloved Son, hear ye him;</hi> Than the Word of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> himſelf, who aſſures us, that his Father and He are but One God, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his Apoſtles to Preach theſe Truths throughout the World; ſaying,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:99316:55"/> that they who believe ſhall be ſaved, and that there is no <hi>Salvation</hi> but in Him.</p>
               <p>For the reaſonableneſs thereof, he may be refer'd to the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves, who though the very Enemies of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> gave ſufficient Teſtimony to his Divinity; when being aſtoniſh'd at the Miracles wrought by Him, they openly profeſs'd, that unleſs a ſtop was put thereto, by ſecuring his Perſon, and forbidding his Doctrine, all Nations would believe in Him. Nor have their Hiſtorians alone, but other Unbelievers alſo, own'd the <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> to be of all others in the World the beſt, theirs only except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; which they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> before it, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through ignorance or prejudice.</p>
               <p>For indeed, what Religion could ever ſhew ſuch Marks and Tokens of the Hand of God, as this of the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> through the whole Courſe of its Propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation? In its firſt Inſtitution, by how many Miracles was it confirm'd? As we find them recorded in the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> by thoſe who were Eye-witneſſes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and whoſe plainneſs and ſimplicity, apparent in all their Relations of the ſame, is proof ſufficient of their Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Nor is it leſs to be admired, how
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:99316:55"/> ſuccesfully it was Preached and Eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, by Perſons of neither Learning, Eloquence, nor Authority; but on the contrary, deſtitute of all outward Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments, expoſed to Poverty, and the Contempt of all Mankind. Who yet by the meer force of Truth, reduced both Learned and Unlearned, whole Empires and Nations, to the ſame <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith;</hi> and under which, by the ſpecial Providence of Almighty God, they have for ſo many Ages been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, notwithſtanding its containing, not only Myſteries above the Reach, but Precepts again the Inclinations and Paſſions of Men's Minds.</p>
               <p>In a Word; That he need not doubt of believing that, which thoſe Bleſſed Spirits ſo divinely proclaim'd, who fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told the Birth of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed it with Songs of Rejoycing, giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Glory to God and promiſing Peace to all Men: Who alſo were Witneſſes of his Reſurrection and Aſcenſion into Heaven. That, which ſo many Saints, and Holy Men and Women, enlighten'd by God, have profeſs'd; which, ſuch vaſt Numbers of the Faithful in all Ages, have by their Mortification and Self-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial, ſacrificed the Pleaſures of this
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:99316:56"/> World to; and through the midſt of ſo many cruel Perſecutions, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained at no leſs a Price, than that of their <hi>Blood;</hi> as knowing what ſure Grounds they were on, even the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority (as we have ſaid before) of God Himſelf, who being Omniſcient, cannot be miſtaken in his knowledge; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the very Truth, cannot deceive or impoſe upon Us by falſe Revelation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> How to comfort a <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> that is miſtruſtful of <hi>God's Mercy,</hi> and troubled with <hi>Deſparing Thoughts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. THE <hi>Miniſter</hi> is to examine the chief Motive of his Diſtruſt; whether it be, that he is ſtill linked to ſome beloved Sin, that he cannot eaſily part with; ſuch as Hatred, or Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, or Carnal Luſt, or the like: Of which we ſhall treat in the Seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Chapter. Or whether there lies ſomething hid in his Heart, which he ought to repent of; the <hi>Miniſter</hi> exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:99316:56"/> him at the ſame time, to make a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Confeſſion of his Sins to God, and throughly bewail them; whereby to remove his diffidence, and ſet his Soul entirely at peace.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If the <hi>Patient</hi> has no Cauſe to miſtruſt God's Goodneſs to him, but is terrified only with the remembrance of his paſt Sins, or the Temptations he is now diſturbed with; then let the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter</hi> excite his Hope; Firſt, towards God, whom he has offended; by telling him, that God is always ready to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give him; That he is a Merciful Father; That his Graces are infinite; That He is full of Tenderneſs and Compaſſion; and that His Love far ſurpaſſes the Sins of Men; That He prevents and aſſiſts us by the inſpirations of his Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and pardons our Iniquities, when we are truly ſorrowful for them. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, towards <hi>Chriſt,</hi> with theſe Words. <q rend="margQuotes">Our Sins, we muſt confeſs, are many and great; but God has laid them all upon <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> by whoſe Sufferings we are redeemed from them. And foraſmuch as we were not able to make Satisfaction for them, by reaſon of our own unworthineſs, his Love for us has extended ſo far, as
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:99316:57"/> to give his only Son to be a <hi>Saviour</hi> to us. His Humility has brought down and deſtroy'd our Pride; His Patience our Paſſions; His Charity our Hatred; His Croſs our Luxury; and His Obedience, even to die for us, has blotted out all our Tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And as the leaſt of his Torments was ſufficient to ſatisfie the Juſtice of God; ſo through theſe infinite Merits of his, may we ask of Him, both the Remiſſion of our Sins, and Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of His Kingdom.</q> Let the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient</hi> for his Comfort, remember; that he is to have for his Judge this ſame <hi>Jeſus,</hi> who is now at the right Hand of God, making Interceſſion for him; and call to mind how gracious He was to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> whom He pardoned almoſt the ſame moment he denied Him. Let him think of the Charitable Words He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced upon the Croſs, on behalf of his very Enemies, <hi>Father, forgive them, for they know not what they do;</hi> and thoſe he ſpake to the Penitent Thief, <hi>That the ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame day he ſhould be with him in Paradiſe.</hi> In ſhort, let him be perſwaded, that God has a greater deſire to ſave him, than he himſelf can have to be ſaved; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he has not the leaſt cauſe to be dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident of his Mercy.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:99316:57"/>3. The <hi>Miniſter</hi> may ſuſtain his Hope and Confidence in God's Goodneſs and Mercy, by the Example of divers Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Perſons, that remitted the injuries done to them, as <hi>Joſeph, David,</hi> St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> and others; teaching him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from, that if theſe who were but Men, had ſo much Meekneſs and Charity, as to forgive their very Perſecutors, what ought not we to expect from God, the Fountain of Mercy? Whoſe Goodneſs will appear ſtill the greater, by how much more numerous the Sins are, which He pardons to us: That there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, provided he has a broken and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite Heart, he needs not in the leaſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend his being rejected or abandon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for though his Tranſgreſſions were more heinous, than thoſe of the Devils themſelves, the <hi>Croſs</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is ſufficient for the aboliſhing of them.</p>
               <p>We do not mean, that the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhould ſay all theſe things at once, and in the Order here preſcribed, as if he made a ſet Diſcourſe to him; but that he uſe his Diſcretion, in ſpeaking them by little and little, and at ſeveral times, according as he ſhall find the <hi>Patient</hi> in a Condition of hearing him, and of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Comfort therefrom. He may
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:99316:58"/> alſo introduce, and relate in few words, the Hiſtory of the Prodigal Son, of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Magdalen,</hi> of the <hi>Samaritan,</hi> and of the <hi>Cananitiſh</hi> Woman, mention'd in the Goſpel; with that of the whole People of the <hi>Jews,</hi> whom God conducted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Land of Promiſe, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their continual Rebellions and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſſes. Let him likewiſe put the <hi>Patient</hi> in mind of the Paſſage in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> where God ſays, He will forget the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities of a Sinner, at what hour ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he ſhall turn and repent: That Pardon is in the Goſpel it ſelf ſecured to us, upon Condition of our forgiving our Enemies; and therefore we ought not to doubt of Forgiveneſs at God's hand, if we for his ſake, freely and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely forgive them that have offended us.</p>
               <p>Thus ſhall the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſupport his Hope, by continually ſaying before him God's Mercies and Promiſes of Pardon to us, for the ſake of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Blood that was ſhed for all Sinners; and aſſuring him, that God will not fail to aſſiſt him by his Grace, nor will ſuffer him to fall away and miſcarry in what concerns his Eternal Salvation. Which having ſaid, and added thereto, what elſe he may
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:99316:58"/> think fit for the ſame purpoſe, he ſhall admoniſh the <hi>Patient</hi> to apply himſelf to God in this manner. <hi>Lord, I am an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful Son; yet ſtill thy Son: Thou having both created me, and adopted me in</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>Thy very Son, Co-ſubſtantial with Thee. O Lord in Thee I have put my truſt, let me never be confounded. I am a prodigal Child; I acknowledg that I have ſinned againſt Heaven and before Thee, and am no more worthy to be called Thy Son. But, O my God! are not Thy Mercies greater than my Tranſgreſſions?</hi> Let him ſay with St. <hi>Anſelm, Lord! though I have kindled luſt in my Heart, can I have quenched Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in Thine? Though I have commited Sins, for which Thou mayſt juſtly condemn me, haſt thou departed from that Goodneſs and Clemency, by which Thou waſt wont to pardon and indulge me? Have mercy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, O my Father! For thine own ſake, and for thy dear Son</hi> Jeſus Chriſt'<hi>s ſake, forgive me all that is paſt. I do earneſtly repent. I am heartily ſorry for all my Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doings. Aboliſh them in the death, and waſh them away in the Blood of my Bleſſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer.</hi> Let him alſo ſay with <hi>Job, Though thou ſhould'ſt kill me, yet will I hope in Thee:</hi> And with <hi>David, Why art Thou ſo vexed, O my Soul, and why art thou diſquieted
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:99316:59"/> within me? O put thy truſt in God, and remember that He is Thy Comfort and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. Lord, enter not into judgment with thy Servant. I fly to thy Clemency; I im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore thy Mercy, not thy Juſtice. Judge me not, O Lord! according to my Deſerts: Deal not with me after my ſins; neither reward me after mine iniquities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All which let the <hi>Patient</hi> be advis'd well to ponder; that from his Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thereupon, which may be ſhorter or longer, according as his pains will allow him more or leſs opportunity for it, he may receive Spiritual Help and Comfort.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, He ſhould be admoniſhed to look up to <hi>Jeſus,</hi> the Author and Finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of our Faith, and God of our Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; to fix in his Mind the continual remembrance of his Sufferings; and break forth to Him in theſe Words. <hi>O Lord, who haſt ſhed thy precious Blood for me, have mercy upon me. Thou Lord, who for the attonement of my ſins, didſt in the midſt of ſo many torments, and with ſo much ignominy, reſign thy Divine Spirit upon the Croſs, have mercy upon me. O Lamb of God, that takeſt away the ſins of the World, have mercy upon me. I commend my Soul to Thee. I commit it into Thy Hands. Lord! receive it. Lord! vouchſafe to ſave it.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:99316:59"/>
               <p>To this the <hi>Miniſter</hi> may add the Words ſet down in the Sixth Chapter, if he judges them neceſſary, for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying of the <hi>Patient</hi>'s Hope, and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring Comfort to him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIV.</hi> What is to be ſaid to ſuch as ſhew too great a Confidence, and preſume too far upon their <hi>Salvation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS the Devil labours nothing more, than the undoing of us to all Eternity; ſo he endeavours to bring this his pernicious Deſign about, by quite contrary Means; ſometimes by ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſting too great a Fear of God's Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſometimes too great a Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in his Mercy. If the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhall perceive, that the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> is flattering himſelf with the good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Works he has done, and ſo from them preſumes too much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his <hi>Salvation,</hi> he ought meekly to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh him to enter into, and recollect himſelf; in order to the making him ſenſible, that our Felicity depends only
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:99316:60"/> upon <hi>Chriſt,</hi> on whom we are wholly to build our Hope of <hi>Salvation:</hi> That God alone enables us to act; and that to Him it is, we owe all the Honour and Glory of our Good Works: That of our ſelves we are but Weakneſs, and capable of nothing that is good, not ſo much as one good Thought, without his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting and aſſiſting Grace: That we ought to give Him Thanks and Praiſe, for what we are, and what we have: That all our Virtue is derived from Him; and that we ſhould find a terrible Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, if when He comes at the laſt Day to judge us, He would look upon our Merits only: That we muſt always re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, what is ſaid in the Goſpel, <hi>That when we have done all that we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to do, we are but unprofitable Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</hi> In a word, that we are bound to God by ſo many Ties of Favours and Bleſſings, that though we ſhould humble our ſelves even to nothing before Him, yet ſhould we be very far from expreſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a due acknowledgment to Him for the ſame.</p>
               <p>But if the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> ſhall ſtill run upon an exceſs of Hope, and rely ſo far upon the Merits of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as not to be at all afflicted or concerned for his
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:99316:60"/> Sins, 'twill be expedient to affright him into a due ſenſe of them; by recalling to his Memory the many Tranſgreſſions of his paſt Life, and ſhewing him the heinouſneſs of them; that ſo he may be made apprehenſive of the neceſſity of a ſincere Repentance and Humiliation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he can expect to obtain Pardon. The <hi>Miniſter</hi> may tell him, that his Hope is laudable; but conſidering what great Sinners we are, we ſhould mix with our Confidence, a Filial Fear, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with Sorrow and Contrition, for our having offended ſo Good, ſo Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and ſo Benign a Father; adding hereto, what further he ſhall think con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducive to the raiſing in him the juſt Notion he ought to have of God's Mercy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:99316:61"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> How a <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> is to be managed, when bereft in a great meaſure, of his <hi>Senſes</hi> and <hi>Underſtanding.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the firſt place, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> is to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form himſelf; whether the <hi>Sick Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> has already been pray'd with, and received the <hi>Holy Communion;</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he has ſet his Houſe and Affairs in order, and thought of every thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for him to do; of which we ſhall ſpeak in the Seventeenth Chapter. If they anſwer him, that nothing has yet been done of all this, as it often happens to thoſe that are backward in preparing themſelves for Death, or are ſtruck on a ſudden with a violent and unforeſeen Diſtemper; he ſhall call to the <hi>Patient</hi> with a loud Voice, and ask him whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he hears him; and if he perceives him to have ſtill ſome remainder of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding he is to advertiſe him of the danger his Life is in, and of the great Concern of his Salvation; which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay (leſt it ſhould prove fatal to him) he ought to ſecure by Repentance
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:99316:61"/> and true Contrition of heart for all the Sins, known and unknown, he has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt his Maker, his Neighbour, and Himſelf; and to reſtore, or cauſe to be reſtored, as far as he is able, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he may have of another Body's. Then he ſhall ask him, whether he be not deſirous to receive the <hi>Bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as well for the Confirmation of his Faith, as Aſſurance of God's Pardon of all his Tranſgreſſions, and intitling him to <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Merits: To which if the <hi>Miniſter</hi> finds him diſpos'd, he ſhall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter it to him, declaring that God has put away his Sins, and will remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them no more; and that the ſame moment this Breath ſhall depart from him, God will receive him to Himſelf, and admit him into the Number of the Righteous that are Sanctified: With whom he ſhall live a Life full of Joy and Bliſs, which never ſhall have end.</p>
               <p>If the <hi>Patient</hi> be in a Condition of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing, which he hath omitted, towards the future ſettlement of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily or Eſtate, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhall adviſe him to do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> now, as we have ſaid elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where: And this done, he ſhall go on with entertaining him in Devotion and Spiritual Contemplations.</p>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:99316:62"/>
               <p>But if the <hi>Miniſter</hi> is told, that the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient</hi> has been already viſited by another, and has received the <hi>Holy Sacrament,</hi> he may ſpare asking him many Queſtions about the State of his Soul (eſpecially if he finds him very weak,) and apply him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf only to the comforting him, and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his Hope and Affections more and more to God, and there fixing them.</p>
               <p>Or if the <hi>Patient</hi> be fallen into a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lirium</hi> or <hi>Lethargy,</hi> the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhall ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wait till he is come to himſelf again, or deſire to have notice, ſo ſoon as thoſe that look after him, ſhall find his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment return'd to him. Which interval of ſenſibleneſs it will concern the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> to improve as much as he is able, by exciting in him, thoſe good Motions and Diſpoſitions that may help him to die in a true State of Regeneration, as well as with ſolid Comfort and Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction: making uſe to that purpoſe, of thoſe means we have propoſed in the preceding Chapters, (particularly in the Eighth) and what elſe in his prudence he ſhall ſee fit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:99316:62"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> What the <hi>Miniſter</hi> is to do, when he finds the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> poſeſs'd of his <hi>Speech</hi> and <hi>Underſtanding,</hi> but likely to die very ſoon.</head>
               <p>WHEN the <hi>Miniſter</hi> is called to One that has receiv'd a mortal Wound, for which no Remedy can be expected, he is to admoniſh him preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to confeſs his Sins, and beg Pardon of God, and all Mankind, whom he has offended, and to be in Charity with the whole World. And if he finds him not throughly affected with the ſenſe of his Offences, nor the danger he is in, he ſhall gently repreſent to him the hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſneſs of his Crimes, and his great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude towards ſo Gracious a God, who has declared Himſelf willing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit all his Tranſgreſſions, upon conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his ſincere Repentance, having ſo loved him as to have given his own Son to die for him. With which Diſcourſe if the <hi>Miniſter</hi> perceives the <hi>Patient</hi> to be moved, and made ſenſible of the Errors
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:99316:63"/> his Life, and truly Penitent, he ſhall give him Confidence in God's Mercies, through the Merits of the ever Bleſſed <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and pronounce to him the ample Pardon, which his Heavenly Father has granted him of all his Sins; and for the yet further confirming him in this Hope, ſhall adminiſter to him the <hi>Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi>'s <hi>Supper,</hi> and continue to exerciſe him in thoſe <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Charity, Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Devotion,</hi> that are mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the foregoing Chapters, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly the Fifth, Sixth, and Seventh.</p>
               <p>If there be any time remaining, the <hi>Patient</hi> ſhall be put in mind, to requeſt the Publick Prayers of the Church, which both the <hi>Miniſter</hi> and his Friends are to take care of procuring for him; that being ſo recommended to God, he may receive the benefit of thoſe Joynt-Prayers, which are moſt prevailing with the Almighty, and as ſuch, may not be a little conducive to the Salvation of his departing Soul.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:99316:63"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> How the <hi>Miniſter</hi> is to apply himſelf to a <hi>Sick Perſon,</hi> who has the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of his <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but no Diſpoſition to ſuch things, as are neceſſary to the making a Happy End.</head>
               <p>WHEN the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> ſhews an unwillingneſs to prepare himſelf, as he ought, for dying well; the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhall deſire his Friends and Relations to put up their earneſt Prayers to God, that He would be pleaſed to touch his heart with a ſenſe of his Sins, and exci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e a true Contrition in him. To which purpoſe, it may alſo be convenient, that ſome of his Friends, in whom he repoſes greateſt Confidence, or ſuch as have influence or Authority over him, apply themſelves to him, and admoniſh him to be atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to what ſhall be ſaid to him in order to his Preparation for Death; that in caſe it ſhould pleaſe God to take himout of this World, he may be forever happy in the next. Then ſhall the <hi>Miniſter</hi>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:99316:64"/> begin with accoſting him in a meek and tender and affectionate manner, by which he may not a little contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to his Salvation: For this will engage him the more readily to give ear to him, and ſo may at length draw him unawares to a ſence of his deplorable Sinful State, and of the abſolute neceſſity of his obtaining Mercy through Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and Faith in <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Merits. And in the next place, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhall repreſent to him, that God does often viſit us with Sickneſs, to awaken us from the ſlumber of Sin, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> did the Man ſick of the <hi>Palſie,</hi> mention'd in the Goſpel; whom (after having heal'd him) he diſcharged with this Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Go and ſin no more, leſt a worſe thing happen to thee:</hi> That God is able ſtill to reſtore him to his former Health, if it ſeem meet to him; but having ſent this Affliction for his amendment, expects he ſhould firſt make that good uſe of it: For the quickening him wherein, he may be put in mind of the Words in <hi>Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> by which we are adviſed not to defer our Converſion one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, leſt Death ſurpriſe us in the midſt of our Sins, and we become thereby ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recoverably loſt. Let him therefore ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:99316:64"/> himſelf inceſſantly to the Buſineſs o his Salvation, and perform the Means neceſſary thereto, while Time and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity ſerve him for them. The ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of which he will very ſoon be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of, in the great Comfort he will draw therefrom, both for appeaſing the Wrath of God, and ſheltering him from the Aſſaults of the Devil. Nor may it be altogether in vain, to excite him to his Duty, by Motives of Honour; tell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, what a Blot it will be to his Reputation; What Shame and Infamy will for ever attend his Name; and of what ill conſequence it may be to his Children and Relations, when it ſhall be remembred, that he died in a State of Sin and Impenitence.</p>
               <p>But if all theſe Admonitions ſhall not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding prove ineffectual, the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter</hi> muſt try to find out the true cauſe of his Obſtinacy; as whether he be an <hi>Atheiſt</hi> or <hi>Infidel,</hi> or has led a looſe and diſſolute Life, and not only committed many enormous Crimes and Immorali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but perſiſted therein for ſeveral Years, without any remorſe or thoughts of Repentance, and for which he thinks there is no Pardon now to be hop'd for; Or whether he has made a Contract
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:99316:65"/> with the Devil; or is ſo tied to ſome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Sin, that he knows not how to bid Farewel to it: Or laſtly, whether it ariſes only from Lazineſs, and the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Examining his Conſcience.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Miniſter</hi> diſcovering that the <hi>Patient</hi> is an <hi>Atheiſt</hi> or <hi>Infidel,</hi> is to lay before him what we have ſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Faith</hi> in the Twelfth Chapter, without entring into any Diſpute with him, unleſs he goes about to maintain his Errors: In which Caſe he muſt be anſwer'd and confuted by ſolid Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But much better it were, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void all diſpute, if poſſible; for fear of exaſperating him, and preventing his coming to that calm and charitable tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of mind, wherein he ought more eſpecially to be at this juncture.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If his Obſtinacy proceeds from the Multiplicity and heinouſneſs of his Crimes, then ſhall the <hi>Miniſter</hi> raiſe his Hope, by what we have ſet down in the Sixth and Thirteenth Chapters; adding for his yet greater Confidence, that were all the Sins both of Men and Devils, joyn'd together in one and the very ſame Perſon, they would appear nothing in compariſon of the Divine Mercy, and might be wholly done-away by one
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:99316:65"/> ſingle Drop of <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Blood: That God knows whereof we are made; He is not ignorant of our Natural Frailty and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſity to Sin; and therefore is ready to pardon us, when-ever we make our application to Him for it, with a truly penitent and contrite heart.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If he has enter'd into a Contract with the Devil, and that is found to be the real cauſe of his Deſpair; the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter</hi> muſt comfort him, and eſtabliſh in him a neceſſary <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Hope; by ſhewing him, that he is not at all oblig'd to keep his Word with ſuch a Traitor and Enemy as that Helliſh Fiend, though he had even ſign'd the Obligation with his own blood; That it is lawful for him to deceive the Deceiver of all Men, and that he ought to fly for ſhelter to his Redeemer, who by his Death, has deliver'd him from the Empire of Satan, and from the Power of Darkneſs; Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereto, what-ever he ſhall think proper to keep up the Patient's Hope, and diſpoſe him, in caſe he be reſtored to Health again, to do what ſhall be directed him for the good of his Soul, and ſecurity of his Eternal Salvation.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If this Obſtinacy proceeds from his adhering to ſome particular Sin, that he
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:99316:66"/> is loath to diſengage himſelf from; ſuch as the being poſſeſs'd of Goods unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully gotten, which he knows not how to think of reſtoring; the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhall repreſent to him, that in all appearance his laſt Minute is now drawing nigh; when he will not be able to avoid leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe Goods behind him, which he refuſes to make Reſtitution of. That his Soul is juſt going to be ſeparated at once from his Body and all thoſe Worldly Pleaſures he ſo fondly embraces, and will not renounce; and that within a little time, he will be ſummon'd before the Tribunal of God, where he muſt expect to receive Sentence, <hi>according as he has done, whether good or bad.</hi> If the fear of leaving his <hi>Children</hi> in want, be the main Obſtruction to his performance of this Eſſential part of his Duty, let him be advis'd to conſider, how great an Enemy he will be to himſelf, thus to expoſe both his Body and Soul to the danger of Everlaſting Flames, only to enrich his <hi>Children;</hi> who, far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the better for this ill-gotten Wealth, may live to curſe it, as an Occaſion of their utter Ruin and Damnation: That indeed, with much greater Pleaſure and Satisfaction, he ſhould caſt them upon
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:99316:66"/> the Divine Providence, who (if they prove Virtuous) will not fail to take careof them, and give them a far better and more ſecure Settlement, than any they could have procured to themſelves, by this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Treaſure: Which joyn'd with a lively Repreſentation of God's infinite Goodneſs and Love to us, the Favours we daily receive from his Hands, and the Glory which He is preparing for us; compared with the dreadful Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Hell, and the miſerable State of the Damned Souls, may prevail upon him to prefer Spiritual Riches and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments, before all other Conſiderations. And as he ſhall be obſerv'd to be moſt affected with any of the foregoing Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, ſuch Motive may be prudently inſiſted on, to the ſoftening of his heart and making it contrite.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> If a drouzy Lazineſs be the Sole Impediment to his Preparation for Death, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhall awaken him from this Spiritual Lethargy, by ſhewing him the great danger his Soul is in; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering him the aſſiſtance of his Advice and Prayers, and exhorting him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs his Sins to God, with a Declaration of God's readineſs to pardon him, on con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of his ſincere and hearty Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:99316:67"/>
               <p>In ſhort, whatever may be the Cauſe of his Reluctance, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhall, as we have ſaid already, deſire his Friends and Relations, not only themſelves to pray for him, but to procure him the Publick Prayers of the Church; not ceaſing to admoniſh the <hi>Patient</hi> alſo, while he is able, to pray for himſelf. Which the <hi>Miniſter</hi> perceiving he is not likely to remain long in a capacity of doing, by reaſon of his approaching Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, he ought by no means to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon him, but on the contrary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>double his Fervor in recommending his Soul to God, and adminiſtring Ghoſtly Comfort to him, to the laſt moment; unleſs it be, that he knows ſome other particular <hi>Miniſter</hi> that may be more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to him; whom in ſuch Caſe, he ſhall cauſe to be ſent for, eſpecially if he be a Man of Authority by his Office and Reputation. By all which Holy Means, and the Bleſſing of God attending them, the <hi>Patient</hi> being brought, as we hope he will, to a through Repentance, and fit Compoſure for receiving it, the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sacrament ſhall be adminiſtred to him; whereby his Conſcience will be much quieted, and his Friends and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations comforted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:99316:67"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> What in the laſt place, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> is to do, if the <hi>Patient</hi> dies; and What, in-caſe it ſhall pleaſe <hi>God</hi> to reſtore him to his <hi>Health</hi> again: With regard on the one hand, to the <hi>Standers-by;</hi> and on the other, to the <hi>Perſon Recover'd.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving conducted the <hi>Patient</hi> through all the Circumſtances of his Illneſs, and (as we hope) left nothing wanting towards the <hi>Security</hi> of his <hi>Everlaſting Salvation;</hi> it remains only, that we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe this <hi>Sickneſs</hi> of his, to terminate ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his <hi>Death</hi> or <hi>Recovery,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the <hi>Miniſter</hi> how to make the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Uſes of both Events.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Death</hi> be the Iſſue; the firſt thing calling for the <hi>Miniſter</hi>'s regard, is the <hi>Comforting</hi> of the <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>Relations</hi> of the <hi>Party Deceas'd. A Subject</hi> ſo copious, that to be particular therein, would be as endleſs as ſuperfluous. I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore content my ſelf, with mentioning ſome of the common <hi>Topicks</hi> of <hi>Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> on this <hi>Occaſion,</hi> and leave it to the
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:99316:68"/> 
                  <hi>Miniſter</hi>'s Diſcretion, to inforce and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large upon them, according to the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of <hi>Perſons, Time,</hi> and <hi>Place.</hi> This then in general may be ſaid to all; That they ought by no means to give way to a <hi>Grief,</hi> that cannot poſſibly avail them any thing; but may, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too far indulg'd, prove both highly diſpleaſing to God, and prejudicial to their own <hi>Healths:</hi> That they are not to look upon thoſe as loſt, whom God is pleas'd to take to Himſelf: And as to this <hi>Separation</hi> from their <hi>Departed Friend,</hi> it will not be of any long continuance; foraſmuch as within a little while they ſhall meet him again in a happy and joyful <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> Nay, that 'tis even ſtill in their power, to poſſeſs him as ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as ever they did, whilſt in the Fleſh, if (as all good <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſhould labour to do) they poſſeſs God, with Whom, and in Whom he now is. On which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, if their Love to him was ſincere, they ought, inſtead of repining at his <hi>Death,</hi> to rejoyce at his being thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd from the <hi>Calamities</hi> and <hi>Miſeries</hi> of this <hi>World,</hi> into the <hi>Boſom</hi> of <hi>Eternal Bliſs</hi> and <hi>Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereby having brought them into a Condition of attending to, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiting
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:99316:68"/> by his <hi>Ghoſtly Admonitions,</hi> the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter</hi> is to repreſent to them, and the reſt of the Company; the Neceſſity of preparing our ſelves for <hi>Death</hi> whilſt we are in <hi>Health,</hi> by frequently receiving of the <hi>Lord</hi>'s <hi>Supper,</hi> and ſtrictly examining our <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Converſations,</hi> eſpecially upon the Article of doing right to our Neighbour, as being that which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly moſt burthens our Conſciences, when we come to die: And how near we may be to this laſt Moment, God only knows, who has number'd our Days, and ſet bounds to our Lives, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond which we ſhall not paſs: That therefore it highly imports us to think ſeriouſly thereon, and ſo to regulate all our Actions, as if we liv'd under a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Expectation of it. Let him ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to them, how precious the preſent time is, and how worthy of being laid hold on for the ſecurity of our Eternal Happineſs. That the Days of Salvation paſs away apace, and when once gone, it being for ever out of our power to recall them again, we ought to employ them with the Care and Circumſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on becoming good <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> by wean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelves, without delay, from the Things of this World, and diſpoſſeſſing
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:99316:69"/> our Hearts of all other Thoughts but what relate to God alone. Nor need we any other Arguments, than the ſight of this very <hi>Dead Body,</hi> to convince us, how vain and tranſiſtory, how deceitful and periſhable, all thoſe falſe Enjoyments are, which the <hi>Devil</hi> makes uſe of to dazzle our Eyes, and allure us to Sin. Neither <hi>Riches,</hi> nor <hi>Honours</hi> are able to procure one Minute's Reſpit from the Stroke of <hi>Death:</hi> When ſhe ſummons, we muſt immediately obey, and quit them all; nay and our very Bodies too, as ſtraightly as we are ty'd to them, and reſign them to unavoidable Corruption. In a word, That the Goods of this World are ſo far only to be deſired, as may ſerve for the neceſſary ſupport of our ſelves, and enable us to be aſſiſting to others.</p>
               <p>From whence he may take occaſion of ſaying ſomething to them, about the Settlement of their Temporal Concerns; adviſing them to make their Wills and Teſtaments, whilſt in a ſtate of perfect Health and Underſtanding; that ſo they may be able to deliberate the more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turely thereon, and diſpoſe of their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, with the greater ſatisfaction to themſelves, as well as Juſtice and Equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:99316:69"/> to others, by a due regard to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, Friendſhip,</hi> and <hi>Deſerts;</hi> it often happening, where this Caution is not us'd, that a <hi>Feaver,</hi> or ſome other vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Diſtemper, ſurpriſes a Man, and puts it out of his power to do the Good he intended to have done: Or ſome of his greedy <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>Relations</hi> finding him in a helpleſs condition, do by their tireſome importunities, oblige him to make an unequal Teſtament: Or laſtly (not to mention more of the many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies ariſing from this neglect) he dies <hi>Inteſtate,</hi> and leaves his Eſtate for a Prey to the <hi>Lawyers,</hi> and a ſtanding occaſion of Diſcord in his Family.</p>
               <p>But when by a prudent, timely, and juſt diſpoſal of his Earthly Poſſeſſions, he has convey'd the Bleſſings of Peace, Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Proſperity to his Family: When by an upright and unſpotted Life, he has preſerved himſelf fit to enter into the <hi>Holy</hi> of <hi>Holies,</hi> the Sacred Manſions of the Moſt High: And laſt of all, when by his Merciful Deeds, he has ſecur'd to himſelf Mercy from his Bleſſed <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour;</hi> Oh! with what unſpeakable Comfort may he end his days, and with what Confidence and Alacrity appear
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:99316:70"/> before the <hi>Tribunal</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> to receive his Everlaſting Reward; applying to himſelf the Words of the <hi>Revelation, I heard a Voice from Heaven ſaying to me, Write, From henceforth bleſſed are the Dead which die in the Lord, even ſo, ſaith the Spirit, for they reſt from their Labours, and their Works follow them.</hi> Thus much in caſe the <hi>Patient</hi> ſhall die.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF it ſhall pleaſe God to reſtore him to his health again:</hi> The <hi>Miniſter</hi> is to viſit and congratulate him thereon; and with ſo much the more fervency, by how much the more dangerous his <hi>Sickneſs</hi> has been. Which will give him the fairer Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of inlarging upon, and rendring him ſenſible of <hi>God's</hi> tranſcendent <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> to him, and the <hi>Gratitude</hi> on his part due for the ſame. <hi>A Debt</hi> (he may tell him) no other ways to be diſcharg'd, than by his making ſuch good uſe of this <hi>Viſitation,</hi> as may tend to the <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Edification</hi> of his <hi>Neighbour,</hi> and the <hi>Amendment</hi> of his own <hi>Life</hi> for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>In order whereto, the <hi>Minister</hi> ſhall remind him of what paſs'd between them during his <hi>Illneſs,</hi> upon the <hi>Subject</hi> of his <hi>Spiritual Welfare:</hi> Of the <hi>Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:99316:70"/> met with in his <hi>Preparation</hi> for <hi>Death,</hi> for want of a timely regard thereto: Of the <hi>Defects</hi> in his <hi>Repentance,</hi> ſtill remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be ſupply'd: Of the particular <hi>Frailties</hi> againſt which he is chiefly to arm himſelf for the time to come: And Laſtly, Of his Pious <hi>Vows</hi> and <hi>Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> (concerning theſe or any other <hi>Points</hi>) founded upon the <hi>Condition</hi> of his <hi>Recovery,</hi> and requiring to be now confirm'd and made good: Adding thereto (to conclude all;) That, as when <hi>Sick,</hi> he deſired and had the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Prayers</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> as well as thoſe of his Private Friends; ſo is it meet and his bounden Duty, that having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Benefit of them, in his <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption</hi> from the <hi>Grave</hi> and the <hi>Gates</hi> of <hi>Death,</hi> he ſhould now <hi>Give Thanks unto the Lord with his whole heart;</hi> not only <hi>ſecretly,</hi> but <hi>among the Faithful, and in the Congregation.</hi> Where he ought alſo with the firſt Opportunity, to <hi>Offer his Vows un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Moſt High, by receiving the Cup of Salvation, and calling upon the Name of the Lord, with humbleſt Supplications,</hi> for the <hi>Aſſiſtance</hi> of his <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> towards enabling him duely to perform the ſame: In the mean time and ever, continuing
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:99316:71"/> fervent in his <hi>Private Devotions,</hi> and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf in ſome meaſure therein, with the <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Thankſgiving</hi> hereto annext. Which <hi>God</hi> of his Infinite Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy accept. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="125" facs="tcp:99316:71"/>
            <head>A <hi>PRAYER</hi> and <hi>THANKSGIVING</hi> to be offer'd to <hi>GOD,</hi> by One newly <hi>Recover'd</hi> from a danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>SICKNESS.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>O MOST GRACIOUS GOD <hi>and</hi> MERCIFUL FATHER! <hi>Who art a</hi> Phyſician <hi>to the</hi> Sick, Strength <hi>to the</hi> Weak, Comfort <hi>to the</hi> Afflicted, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief <hi>to the</hi> Needy, <hi>and</hi> Succour <hi>to the</hi> Helpleſs, <hi>I Thy poor Wretched Creature, having ſo deeply taſted of Thy Mercies, do with a profound ſenſe of Thine Infinite Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and of my own unworthineſs, yeild Thee moſt humble and hearty Thanks and Praiſe, for Thy manifold Benefits and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours towards me; and particularly, for that Thou haſt been pleaſed in ſo fatherly a manner to viſit me, and to bring me back from the</hi> Grave, <hi>and from the</hi> Gates <hi>of</hi> Death; <hi>reſtoring me to my former Health and Strength.</hi> LORD! <hi>What ſhall I render unto Thee, as for all other, ſo more eſpecially for this tender Mercy of thine, in thus ſparing me longer in the</hi> Land of the Living, <hi>and affording me ſtill a larger ſpace for my Repentance?</hi> Thou haſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten'd and corrected me, but haſt not
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:99316:72"/> given me over unto Death. Thou hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not Thy Face from me, when I was in trouble. Thou haſt not made my Life like them that go down into the pit, nor caſt Thy Servant away in Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. O <hi>ſanctifie this Thy Fatherly Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to me, that it may prove an effectual Means for my Thorough-amendment! And grant, I humbly beſeech Thee, that through the Aſſiſtance of Thy Divine Spirit, I may be enabled hereafter to make ſuch good uſe of the Time, which Thy unſpeakable Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs hath now inlarged to me, and ſo husband and improve the ſame, to Thy Service, as that it may not repent Thee to have lent it me. Grant that I may ſeriouſly ponder and admire Thy tranſcendent Favours to me, and my juſt Obligations of Gratitude to Thee, as well as Encouragement continually to depend upon Thee; and may without further delay, ſet about the Buſineſs Thou hast appointed for me here, even the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Buſineſs <hi>of my</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Salvation: <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> I may ſpend the precious Remainder of my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ife, in a conſtant practice of my Duty towards Thee,</hi> O MY GOD, <hi>and towards my Neighbour, and my ſelf; That I may redeem the time which (alas!) I have ſo unworthily miſpent, by living in ignorance, and after the Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Vanities of the World; And that
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:99316:72"/> conſidering, how ſhort this my time is</hi> (which is but a Vapour that vaniſhes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way) <hi>I may never imploy it</hi> in making proviſion for the Fleſh, to fulfil the luſts thereof; <hi>but</hi> live in Righteouſneſs, Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and Holineſs, <hi>all my days: That I may apply my Heart to that true Wiſdom, which is to know and ſerve Thee; That I may begin even here on Earth, that bleſſed Work I ſhall continue in Heaven to all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity; namely, to love and adore Thee, and to walk before Thee with all humility and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs; to Praiſe, Laud, and Magnifie Thy Holy Name, for Thy great Glory, and for Thy Goodneſs-ſake. Inlighten my mind, that I may have a more perfect Knowledge of Thee, and inflame my heart with a greater Love towards Thee.</hi> Teach me to do the thing that pleaſes Thee; for Thou art my God: Let Thy loving Spirit lead me forth into the Land of Righteouſneſs. <hi>O give me grace to do Thy Will in all Things, and to delight in nothing more, than in obeying Thy Laws and Commandments; wherein there is</hi> Great Pleaſure, <hi>and</hi> Great Reward. <hi>And to all the Favours I have already received at Thy Merciful Hand,</hi> LORD! <hi>Vouchſafe to add this one more; That I may never depart from Thee, or be abandoned by Thee;
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:99316:73"/> but that I may in my whole</hi> Life <hi>pleaſe Thee, and in my</hi> Death <hi>praiſe Thee: That when ever Thou ſhalt ſee fit to call me out of this World, I may be ready to obey Thy Heavenly Summons, and to follow Thee, and be admitted into Thine Everlaſting Kingdom of Bliſs and Glory, with this moſt ſweet and comfortable Invitation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of my</hi> BLESSED SAVIOUR's, Well done, Good and Faithful Servant: Enter thou into the Joy of thy Maſter. <hi>Grant this</hi> O MERCIFUL FATHER! <hi>for Thine own ſake, and for the ſake of this Dear Son of Thy Love, for whom I, and all that is within me, give Praiſe and Adoration to Thee; and in whoſe most prevailing Name, I further implore Thy Divine Majesty; humbly and earnestly praying, as He Himſelf has taught me in his Holy Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
